<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>How to write disambiguation files</title>

  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>How to write disambiguation files</title>

      <section>
        <title>Constraint grammar</title>

        <p>The main introduction to CG-2 is Tapanainen 1996. Karlsson &amp; al
        1992 gives a good introduction to CG-1, and also the most thorough
        presentation of the philosophy behind the constraint grammar
        framework.</p>

        <p>The projects uses the CG-2 formalism, and this formalism is
        presentation below. The concrete implementation is vislcg.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The structure of the disambiguation file</title>

        <p>The disambiguation file has the suffix .rle, in our case it is
        called sme-dis.rle, smj-dis.rle, etc. The file consists of the
        following sections (an additional section CORRECTIONS may also be
        used, it then follows the CONSTRAINTS sections):</p>

        <ul>
          <li>DELIMITERS</li>

          <li>SETS</li>

          <li>MAPPINGS</li>

          <li>CONSTRAINTS (there are several CONSTRAINT sections</li>
        </ul>

        <section>
          <title>The delimiters</title>

          <p>There are four delimiters, ".", "?", "" and "!". The section thus
          contains the following line only:</p>

          <source>DELIMITERS = "&lt;.&gt;" "&lt;!&gt;" "&lt;?&gt;" "&lt;¶&gt;";</source>

          <p>The last delimiter is inserted by the corpus processor in order
          to single out titles and other headings.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>The lists and sets</title>

          <p>This section is introduced with the heading SETS. Note that this
          heading must be removed in order to run the parser with Connexor's
          parser mdis.</p>

          <p>The tags are introduced to the parser as lists and sets. Tags or
          tag combinations that are not introduced here must be referred to
          within parentheses. Lists and sets are defined according to the
          following principles:</p>

          <ol>
            <li>Every grammatical tag used in the rules as such should be
            declared as a one-membered LIST carrying its own name. This in
            order to be able to refer to them without using parenteses. Thus,
            we now have SELECT N IF (-1 V); instead of SELECT (N) IF (-1
            (V)).</li>

            <li>Tag combinations, such as (N Sg) or (Pron Pers Sg1 Nom) are
            not defined as single-membered LISTs, but referred to as tags
            (hence in parentheses). Note: Should frequent tag combinations get
            a list and thereby a shorter name? e.g. LIST MUN = (Pron Pers Sg1
            Nom); ?</li>

            <li>Sets of different tags and/or combinations are declared as
            sets, e.g. SET ADVLCASE = Ill | Loc | Com | Ess. Note: Should they
            be declared as lists, e.g. LIST ADVLCASE = Ill Loc Com Ess ;? In
            this case they are of course a list of tags, and not a set of
            (atomic) sets. Which method is preferrable?</li>

            <li>Finally, the sets on which there are other operations than OR
            (such as + and -) are declared as SETs.</li>
          </ol>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>barriers</title>

          <p>Barriers are used to constrain the scope of rule contexts. By
          now, there are so many complex barrier sets, that a systematic
          documentation of barriers, their linguistic implications and
          consequences of their use might be necessary for rule writers. Often
          enough, we barriers turned out to implement other linguistic
          barriers than originally expected.</p>

          <p>Another fact is that until now complex barriers do not exist. So,
          we actually talk about signal words rather than barriers denoting a
          particular construction.</p>

          <section>
            <title>ambiguos barriers</title>

            <p>CC</p>

            <ol>
              <li>can introduce another main clause</li>

              <li>can introduce another noun phrase in coordination</li>

              <li>can introduce another modifier of a noun phrase within a
              noun phrase</li>
            </ol>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>phrase structure philosophy</title>

            <p>SET S-BOUNDARY = CP | CS | SEMICOL | COL  ;<br /># remember
            that (",") and CC are potential sentence boundaries, too</p>

            <p>SET NP-BOUNDARY = CC | COMMA ;<br /># remember that those are
            potential sentence boundaries, too</p>

            <p>SET BOUNDARY = S-BOUNDARY OR NP-BOUNDARY ;</p>

            <p>SET CRD = COMMA | CC | NEGFOC | XGO ; <br /># coordinators</p>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>formalism oriented</title>

            <p>Since we get formalism caused problems, such as eingschobene
            phrases, that again fullfill other barrier criteria and therefore
            have the consequence that a certain construction is not
            recognized.</p>

            <p>SET INTR = REL | MO | PUNCT-LEFT ;<br />#
            interupters</p>

            <p>SET NPNH:<br />This set - a negation of the set PRE-NP-HEAD -
            originally denotes words, that are no possible modifiers of an NP.
            But: sometimes NPNH is used as a BARRIER at a point of time (or
            rather order) in the rule file we still have the Acc option to
            Gen, if NPNH is used as a BARRIER we do not get the rule to work
            since Acc is not a member of the set PRE-NP-HEAD.</p>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>The constraints</title>

          <p>The constraints of the North Saami file are documented <a
          href="/lang/sme/docu-sme-dis.html">here</a>.</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The format of the constraint rules</title>

        <p>tbw.</p>
      </section>

      
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
