<html xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en">
   <head>
      <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8">
      <title>Metadata files for corpus files</title>
   </head>
   <body>
      <h1>XSL-files</h1>
      <p>
         The purpose of the xsl files is:
         
      </p>
      <ul>
         <li>
            Add metadata about the original file. Examples of this is info
            about the author, publishing year, which language it has been
            translated from, who added the file to the repository, pointers
            to parallel files, etc.
            
         </li>
         <li>
            Add info about which parts of a document to exclude or include.
            This especially handy for pdf documents, which is a fickly file
            format to convert to xml. There is also support to do the same
            for clean text, html and epub files.
            
         </li>
         <li>
            Add processing instructions, such as the languages
            to which the text is categorized or some information of the text
            layout.
            
         </li>
      </ul>
      <p>The xsl-file is created when a file is added to a
         <a href="corpus_repositories.html">corpus repository</a>
         using
         <a href="/ling/CorpusTools.html#add_files_to_corpus">add_files_to_corpus</a>.
         The xsl-file is stored to the same directory as the original
         document, with the same name as the original document, and suffix <code>.xsl</code>.
         
      </p>
      <p>The variables are defined by expressions as the following:</p>
      <pre xml:space="preserve">
&lt;xsl:variable name="title" select="''"/&gt;
&lt;xsl:variable name="author" select="''"/&gt;
&lt;xsl:variable name="author-gender" select="'f'"/&gt;
&lt;xsl:variable name="publisher" select="''"/&gt;
&lt;xsl:variable name="translated-from" select="''"/&gt;

&lt;xsl:variable name="mainlang" select="'sme'"/&gt;
            </pre>
      <p>The information is updated by adding the new value to the
         "select"-field, inside single quotes. Most of the fields, such as
         the title and the name of the author can contain free text, but the
         values of some fields are restricted.
      </p>
      <p>
         The template for the xsl files is
         <a href="https://gtsvn.uit.no/langtech/trunk/tools/CorpusTools/corpustools/xslt/XSL-template.xsl">$GTHOME/tools/CorpusTools/corpustools/xslt/XSL-template.xsl</a>.
         How to fill in values are documented in that document.
         
      </p>
   </body>
</html>