<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Corpus collector's manual</title>

    <authors>
      <person email="tomi.pieski@hum.uit.no" name="Tomi Pieski" />

      <person email="saara huhmarniemi @ helsinki fi" name="Saara Huhmarniemi" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>This file provides an overview of the corpus conversion process.
      Basically, when a new document is recieved, it is classified according
      the language and genre and stored as such to the directory structure for
      the original files. All the original files are left untouched. The text
      and structural information contained in the document is extracted by a
      conversion script and transformed to an xml-file. Xml-files are stored
      in separate directory hierarchy where they can be easily accessed and
      used as a test material for grammar checkers and spellers. The
      metainformation associated with the document, such as the name of the
      author, is stored in an xsl-file and appended to the xml-file during the
      conversion. The metainformation is used elsewhere, in different corpus
      applications.</p>

      <p>First section explains the conversion process step by step. It is
      followed by more detailled descriptions of the directory structure and
      the handling of the file-specific xsl-files. There is also a small
      section of the log-files and the different uses of the convert2xml.pl
      -script.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Basic conversion process</title>

      <p>When you have a file that you want to add to our corpus directory,
      you have two alternatives. You can either use the web upload script in
      <a
      href="http://www.divvun.no/upload/upload_corpus_file.html">http://www.divvun.no/upload/upload_corpus_file.html</a>
      or insert the file manually.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Web upload script</title>

        <p>Open the page <a
        href="http://www.divvun.no/upload/upload_corpus_file.html">http://www.divvun.no/upload/upload_corpus_file.html</a>.</p>

        <ol>
          <li>Choose the file you want to upload, or specify the url.</li>

          <li>Choose the license type for the text: "free", which means that
          the text is free to use by everyone, "standard" which denotes the
          license that is specified in the contracts with text provides or
          "other", when some other than the standard license will be used (the
          information has to be added manually later).</li>

          <li>Fill in the metainformation. The uploading takes a while
          especially if the file is large or with lot of structure. After
          submitting the form, a page will open with fields for filling the
          metainformation. The fields "language" and "genre" are obligatory.
          If you nevertheless feel unsecure about the genre of the document,
          you may leave it open, but please inform the maintainers about
          that.</li>

          <li>If any problems persist, please contact the maintainers. You
          will be informed on how the uploading succeeded.</li>
        </ol>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manual conversion</title>

        <p>If you have a file that you want to add to the corpus repository by
        hand</p>

        <ol>
          <li>Start with determining the main language: <code>eng, fin, nno,
          nob, sma, sme, smj, swe. </code>And genre: <code>admin, bible,
          facta, ficti, laws, news.</code>See section directory structure for
          details.</li>

          <li>Copy the file to the directory
          /usr/local/share/corp/orig/$lang/$genre/. (Check that there isn't
          already a file with the same name.) (there should perhaps be a
          md5sum test for the files here as well, add it to convert2xml). For
          example, a North Sámi document in genre "facta", copy the file to
          directory /usr/local/share/corp/orig/sme/facta/. For news genre,
          there are subdirectories for different sources of news, and for
          bible texts, there are subdirectories for ot and nt.</li>

          <li><p>Run the convert2xml.pl script for the file. For example, a MS
          Word document, with language and genre as above, is converted with
          command (relative path is fine as well, but do not use tilde.) Give
          the language as command line option.</p>
<source>
convert2xml.pl --lang=sme --dir=/usr/local/share/corp/orig/sme/facta/ file_name.doc
</source>

          <p>The
          conversion takes a while especially if the file is large or with lot
          of structure. If you want to see all the error messages generated
          during conversion, use option --nolog.</p></li>

          <li>Check out the resulting xml-file in the corresponding
          bound-directory. If there are fatal errors during the conversion,
          you will see an error message stating "ERROR &lt;something&gt;",
          consult the maintainers of the corpus files or see the log file (in
          /usr/local/share/corp/tmp) for details. The script informs you of
          the character conversion and the original (or intermediate)
          encoding.</li>

          <li><p>Update the metainformation by editing the file
          /usr/local/share/corp/orig/$lang/$genre/file_name.xsl. The file is
          under version control, so check it out for writing with
          command</p><source>     co -l file_name.xsl</source><p>Specify the
          values for fields that are incorrect or missing by giving a value to
          the corresponding variable. Check in your changes with
          command:</p><source>     ci -m"your log message" xsl-file.xsl </source></li>

          <li>Run the convert2xml.pl script once more to get the changes to
          the xml-file.</li>
        </ol>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The directory structure</title>

      <p>The corpus is situated on the machine victorio.uit.no. The two main
      directories in the corpus are <em>orig</em> and <em>bound</em>.
      <em>orig</em> contains the original files with the original names (bar
      spaces replaced with _) and in the original format. The file-specific
      xsl-files are in under the orig-hierarchy as well, in the same
      subdirectory as the document itself.<em>bound</em> has the same
      structure as <em>orig</em>, but contains the files converted from the
      original format to our internal xml-format. The bound-directory contains
      copies of all the files in the corpus database, with restricted access
      only for the project team members. There is a directory
      <code>free</code> for the xml-versions of the documents that are freely
      available. If the access to the document is restricted, the conversion
      updates only the version in the bound-hierarchy. If the document is
      marked as publicly available, both bound- and free-directories are
      updated.</p>

      <p>Inside these directories are directories for various languages. They
      contain parallell translations to the sami documents. Below is an
      outline of the directory structure.</p>

      <source>
                
/usr/local/share/corp/
                    orig/
                        eng/
                        fin/
                        nob/
                        sma/
                        sme/
                        smj/
                        swe/
                    bound/
                        eng/
                        fin/
                        nob/
                        sma/
                        sme/
                        smj/
                        swe/
            </source>

      <p>Inside each of the language directories the structure outlined below
      is used.</p>

      <source>
                
admin/
    depts/
    guovda/
    karas/
    others/
    sd/
bible/
    ot/
    nt/
facta/
ficti/
laws/
news/
    Assu
    MinAigi
    NRK
    YLE
    other
            </source>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>XSL-files</title>

      <p>The subdirectories under orig contain the original documentes stored
      to the corpus database in their original format (doc, pdf, txt, html and
      paratext at the moment). During the conversion, the original documents
      are transformed to text and stored in an xml-structure. The xml-files
      are stored under bound-hierarchy, whereas the original documents stay
      unthouched. The conversion from the original format to the xml-file can
      be done any time, and should be done if e.g the tools improve or the
      xml-structure changes.</p>

      <p>The xml-document contains a header for the metainformation such as
      the title of the document, author(s), publication info and so on. Since
      we cannot edit the original document and do not want to edit the
      xml-file, the changes to the metasection are done in an xsl-script,
      which adds the metainformation to the xml-file during the conversion. In
      addition to metainformation, the xsl-file may contain processing
      instructions, such as the languages to which the text is categorized or
      some information of the text layout.</p>

      <p>The xsl-file is created during the conversion by the
      convert2xml-script. When the corpus file is uploaded to the directory
      hierarchy via web interface, the script xsl-process.cgi creates the
      xsl-file. The xsl-file is stored to the same directory as the original
      document, with the same name as the original document, and suffix
      .xsl.</p>

      <p>File specific xsl-file contains variables for main language and
      metainformation of the corpus document. By changing or adding values on
      these variables, we are able modify the the xml-file without touching
      the original.</p>

      <section>
        <title>The variables in the xsl-file</title>

        <p>The variables are defined by expressions as the following:</p>

        <source>&lt;xsl:variable name="title" select="''"/&gt;
&lt;xsl:variable name="author" select="''"/&gt;
&lt;xsl:variable name="author-gender" select="'f'"/&gt;
&lt;xsl:variable name="publisher" select="''"/&gt;
&lt;xsl:variable name="translated-from" select="''"/&gt;

&lt;xsl:variable name="mainlang" select="'sme'"/&gt;
</source>

        <p>The information is updated by adding the new value to the
        "select"-field, inside single quotes. Most of the fields, such as the
        title and the name of the author can contain free text, but the values
        of some fields are restricted. The variables are explained in detail
        in following.</p>

        <section>
          <title>General variables</title>

          <dl>
            <dt><code>filename</code></dt>

            <dd>The original name of the file, that comes from the submitter
            of the document. Sometimes the filename has to be changed e.g. for
            the system requirements: no white spaces or special characters are
            allowed in the filename.</dd>

            <dt><code>author1_fn, author1_ln, author1_born,
            author1_nat</code></dt>

            <dd>Information of the first author: first name, last name, date
            or year of birth, nationality. The variables for author2 etc.
            respectively.</dd>

            <dt><code>author1_gender</code></dt>

            <dd>The gender is selected from the list: f, m or unknown.</dd>

            <dt><code>translated_from</code></dt>

            <dd>The original language of the document: select from the list:
            sme, smj, sma, nob, nno, fin, ger, eng, .. and so on.</dd>

            <dt><code>publChannel</code></dt>

            <dd>The values are either: published or unpublished</dd>

            <dt><code>publisher, place, collection, ISBN, ISSN</code></dt>

            <dd>The name of the publisher, place, the name of the collection
            etc. as free text.</dd>

            <dt><code>year</code></dt>

            <dd>Publishing year, or if the document is unpublished, the year
            the document was written.</dd>

            <dt><code>translator_fn, translator_ln, translator_gender,
            translator_nat, translator_born</code></dt>

            <dd>The values are similar as with the author1.</dd>

            <dt><code>license_type</code></dt>

            <dd>The availability of the document. Some documents are freely
            available, some are under license. The type of the license is
            either free, standard or other.</dd>

            <dt><code>sub_name, sub_email</code></dt>

            <dd>The name and email of the submitter.</dd>

            <dt><code>wordcount</code></dt>

            <dd>The wordcount for size estimates.</dd>

            <dt><code>metadata</code></dt>

            <dd>If the xsl-file is finished. The values are complete and
            uncomplete</dd>

            <dt><code>template_version, current_version</code></dt>

            <dd>Version information of the original XSL-template and the
            version number of the current xsl-file. This information is
            provided automatically.</dd>

            <dt><code>note</code></dt>

            <dd>Free text field for notes.</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>The languages of the document</title>

          <dl>
            <dt><code>mainlang</code></dt>

            <dd>The main language of the document: sme, smj, sma, nob, fin,
            etc. The main language should be the same as the language
            directory where the file is in.</dd>
          </dl>

          <dl>
            <dt><code>monolingual, multilingual</code></dt>

            <dd>Select "1" for either of these. If both are undefined, the
            document is assumed to be multilingual.<dl>
                <dt>mlang_sme, mlang_nob, mlang_fin, mlang_swe,..</dt>

                <dd>The languages that appear in the document in addition to
                the main language.</dd>
              </dl></dd>
          </dl>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Parallel texts</title>

          <dl>
            <dt>parallel_texts</dt>

            <dd>Select "1" if the document has parallel texts.</dd>
          </dl>

          <dl>
            <dt>para_sme, para_nob, para_fin, para_swe</dt>

            <dd>Give the names of the parallel documents. The parallel file is
            assumed to be located in the corresponding subdirectory under the
            selected language. E.g. the Bokmål paralle file of the
            file<code>corp/orig/sme/facta/file.doc</code> is assumed to be
            located in <code>corp/orig/nob/facta/</code>. If this is not the
            case, give the full path to the file. If more than one document in
            some language correspond the document, give the filenames
            separated by comma (,).</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Other processing instructions in the xsl-file.</title>

        <section>
          <title>Changing the language of a paragraph</title>

          <p>It is possible to explicitely state that some element in the
          xml-document is categorized to some language. The part of xsl-file
          that specifies the block is the following:</p>

          <source>&lt;!-- Add all paragraphs that should have xml:lang=X--&gt;
&lt;!-- Uncomment the following and add the paths, for example: --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;xsl:template match="/root/section[2]/paragraph[5] |
                      /root/section[3]/paragraph[2] "&gt; --&gt;

&lt;xsl:template match=""&gt;
    &lt;xsl:element name="p"&gt;
    &lt;xsl:attribute name="xml:lang"&gt;
        &lt;xsl:value-of select="$smelang"/&gt;
    &lt;/xsl:attribute&gt;
    &lt;xsl:apply-templates/&gt;
&lt;/xsl:element&gt;
&lt;/xsl:template&gt;</source>

          <p>Change the value of "template match" to the XPath-expression of
          the xml-element. Change the value of "select" to the desired
          language.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Translating characters to other characters in the
          text</title>

          <p>The problematic characters in the document that cannot be reached
          by the character conversion can be replaced by xsl-script. The line
          of code is:</p>

          <source>&lt;xsl:value-of select="translate($text,'ðq','đá') "/&gt;</source>

          <p>In the example, the ð is translated to đ and q to á.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Excluding a file from conversion</title>

          <p>The xsl-file contains line for including the processing
          instructions:</p>

          <source>&lt;xsl:include href="/usr/local/share/corp/bin/common.xsl"/&gt;</source>

          <p>Sometimes the converted text does not fulfill the quality
          requirements for some reason, e.g. the Sámi characters are missing
          or encoded strangely. The file can be excluded from the conversion
          by replacing "common.xsl" with "empty.xsl".</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>XSL-files and version control</title>

        <p>xsl-files are under RCS version control, which is indicated by the
        suffix <code>,v</code>. A revision must be checked out for reading and
        processing as well as for editing. The relevant commands for handling
        the version control are described in the following:</p>

        <source>   co xsl-file.xsl     # Check out the file for reading or processing (the file is write protected).
   co -l xsl-file.xsl  # Check out the file for editing, creates a lock.
   ci -m"your log message" xsl-file.xsl     # Check in the file, remove the lock. </source>

        <p>Sometimes people check out files and forget to check them in again,
        thus keeping the file locked. If so, ask the owner of the lock to
        remove it or it that is not possible, steal the lock with <code>rcs
        -u</code>see the rcs man page for details. The RCS files can be
        accessed by anyone belonging to the cvs group. The files can also be
        deleted by persons belonging to the cvs group, so beware! Check the
        permissions.. todo.</p>

        <p>If you create an xsl-file manually, use the following command to
        add the initial revision under version control:</p>

        <source>   ci -t-"log message" -q -i xsl-file.xsl</source>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Log files</title>

      <p>The error messages, warnings and other information of the conversion
      are stored in special logfile. The log file is named after current date
      and time and stored to a temporary directory, by default the directory
      tmp/ under corpdir. The directory can be given as a command line option
      as well. The log file contains the information that was printed to
      STDERR during the conversion. The errors that prevent some document to
      be converted are still printed to the screen as well. If you want all
      the errors to be printed to screen, use option --nolog. The log file is
      for example:<code> tmp/Feb-10-8-57.log</code></p>

      <p>The old log files are stored to a compact format under
      /usr/local/share/corp/tmp/log/. There you can look for the log file from
      the day the current xml-document was created. To examine the tar-file
      from 10th of February, first copy the tar-file to your home directory
      and then open it:</p>

      <source>    cp tmp/log/2006-Feb/Feb-10.tar.gz ~/tmp/
    gunzip tmp/log/2006-Feb/Feb-10.tar.gz
    tar -xvf tmp/log/2006-Feb/Feb-10.tar.gz</source>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>convert2xml.pl</title>

      <p>There are several options available which control the conversion
      process, it is e.g possible to skip the xsl-processing, the character
      decoding, or the hyphenation. The available options:</p>

      <source>
Usage: convert2xml.pl [OPTIONS] [FILES]
The available options:
    --xsl=&lt;file&gt;    The xsl-file which is used in the conversion.
                    If not specified, the default values are used.
    --dir=&lt;dir&gt;     The directory where to search for converted files.
                    If not given, only FILE is processed.
    --tmpdir=&lt;dir&gt;  The directory where the log and other temporary files are stored.
    --nolog         Print error messages to screen, not to log files.
    --corpdir=&lt;dir&gt; The corpus directory, default is /usr/local/share/corp.
    --no-decode     Do not decode the characters.
    --multi-coding  Resolve the character coding separately for each paragraph.
    --no-hyph       Do not add &lt;hyph/&gt; tags.
    --no-xsl        Skip the file-specific xsl-processing.
    --all-hyph      Tag all hyphens (default is at the end of the line).
    --no-hyph       Do not tag hyphens.
    --upload        Do conversion in the upload-directory.
    --lang          The main language of the document.
    --help          Print this message and exit.
</source>

      <p>The file to be converted is given to convert2xml.pl as command line
      argument. The behaviour can be changed by giving the --dir, then the
      directory specified is searched for files to be converted. The file
      types that are supported at the moment are: doc, pdf, html, text and
      paratext. The corresponding file suffixes are are .doc, .pdf, .html, txt
      and .ptx. At the users' point of view, there is no difference between
      the file types, the technical documentation is provided at <a
      href="corpus_conversion_tech.html">corpus_conversion_tech.html</a>.</p>

      <p>The script convert2xml.pl is mainly used for the basic corpus
      directory hierarchy, but it can be configured for other environments as
      well. How this is done is explained in the following:</p>

      <p>Some documents get wrongly utf-8-encoded by the conversion tools and
      they are fixed using a Perl module <code>samiChar::Decode.pm. </code>It
      is installed in victorio, and you should not notice it's presence. If
      you are converting files in some other machine, you should install the
      module.. Another Perl module that is needed is XML::Twig. Instructions
      for installing both modules can be found in <a
      href="corpus_conversion_tech.html">corpus_conversion_tech.html.</a></p>

      <p>Let the original file be <code>original.pdf</code>. Use for example
      the command</p>

      <source>
  $ perl convert2xml.pl --corpdir=/home/mydir/samipdf --tmpdir=mytmp original.pdf
</source>

      <p>Generally each file has only one character coding which may be
      wrongly utf-8-encoded. The best way to decode the file is determined
      statistically. By using the option --multi-coding, the file is assumed
      to contain more than one character codings, which are decoded
      paragraph-wise.</p>

      <p>The resulting file is fully converted xml-file <code>
      original.pdf.xml </code>When working with the full directory hierarchy,
      the original file is expected to be found in some subdirectory under
      /usr/local/share/corp/orig. Then the resulting xml-file is generated to
      the corresponding subdirectory under /usr/local/share/corp/bound. If you
      have the same hierarchy in the corpdir given in commandline, the process
      will be similar. You may use relative path names to the files and
      directories but do not use tilde (~).</p>

      <p>The hyphenation points are tagged as <code>&lt;hyph/&gt; </code>. The
      script tags hyphens that are found at line breaks or end of the
      paragraphs followed by a suitable word. If all the hyphenation points
      should be tagged, convert2xml.pl can be called with option
      --all-hyph.</p>
    </section>

    <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by
    $Author$</p>
  </body>
</document>