<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
   <header>
      <title>Corpus infrastructure</title>
      <authors>
         <person email="trond.trosterud@uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
      </authors>
   </header>
   <body>
      <section>
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <warning>The corpus infrastructure documentation is partly outdated</warning>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Short note on status quo</title>
         <p>We are in the middle of rebuilding our conversion routines. The philosophy is the same as before, but the
         actual conversion is different. Stay tuned.</p>
         <p>While waiting for a documetation rewrite this intro document will contain some notes on how to convert the
         corpus on your own machine. Eventually, the content below will be put in more appropriate places.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Conversion, notes on usage</title>
         <p>The corpus is now under svn. Check out the original files, and convert to xml. The conversion process will
         take a couple of hours. The command is as follows (issued when standing in the <code>freecorpus</code> (or on
         victorio: the <code>boundcorpus</code>) catalogue.</p>
         <p><code>find orig -type f | grep -v .svn | grep -v xsl | grep -v '~|xargs convert2xml2.pl 2&gt;/dev/null
         </code></p>
         <p>If you convert on mac, the following grep command should be added: | grep -v '.DS_Store', to give this
         command:</p>
         <p><code>find orig -type f | grep -v .svn | grep -v xsl | grep -v ~| grep -v '.DS_Store'|xargs convert2xml2.pl
         2&gt;/dev/null </code></p>
         <p>The graphical show that follows indicate lines looking like this: "...|......". Here, each symbol represents
         a file. The dots indicate "(formally) successful conversion", and the pipe symbols indicate flawed conversion.
         Note that the conversion will be flawed if you are offline while converting, as the conversion scripts takes
         the dtd from the net (we should consider making this more robust). The conversion script converts some thousand
         files at a time, it then looks as if it starts again, but in reality it just "takes a new bite" and carries on
         the conversion. </p>
         <p>Now, you might want to check the content. The converted xml files are found in the converted/ catalogue.
         Scripts for more detailed checks are found in <code>$GTHOME/gt/scripts/corpus/</code>.</p>
         <fixme author="Børre">Consider documenting them, or at least giving hints as to purpose (in case it does not
         follow from the file name), and indicate which ones are obsolete.</fixme>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Catches</title>
         <p>This section should document the fixes needed in order to get the conversion working on your machine.</p>
         <ul>
            <li>Correct java versjon</li>
            <li>New grep version</li>
            <li>...</li>
         </ul>
         <p></p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Usage</title>
         <p>The command for using the corpus is:</p>
         <p><code>ccat -l sma -r converted/sma/ | less</code></p>
         <p>This command will give you all the South Sami content of the converted South Sami files. The ccat utility is
         documented somewhere.</p>
         <p></p>
         <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by $Author:
         boerre $</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Old links (kept for now)</title>
         <p><a href="corpus_dtd.html">DTD -discussion</a></p>
         <p><a href="corpus_conversion.html">Conversion</a></p>
      </section>
   </body>
</document>
