<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
	<header>
		<title>Corpus repositories</title>

		<authors>
		<person email="borre.gaup@samediggi.no" name="Børre Gaup" />
		</authors>
	</header>

	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Corpus repositories</title>

			<p>
				The corpus is divided in a free part, where texts that we can redistribute are
				gathered, and a bound part, where we gather texts that we can't redistribute.
			</p>

			<section>
				<title>The free part</title>

				<p>
					The free part is available in an svn repository that is world readable
					available on the address
					<a href="https://victorio.uit.no/freecorpus/">https://victorio.uit.no/freecorpus/</a>.
				</p>

				<p>
					Check out a working copy either by adding the above address to
					your svn program, or use the command line program like this:
					<code>svn checkout https://victorio.uit.no/freecorpus</code>.
				</p>
			</section>

			<section>
				<title>The bound part</title>

				<p>
					The bound part is available in an svn repository that is
					accessible only from the machine victorio.uit.no. This
					repository is readable by people that have signed
					<a href="">our non disclosure agreement</a>, and is writable
					by the corpus maintainers. The address to this repository is
					svn://victorio.uit.no/boundcorpus.
				</p>

				<p>
					To check out a working copy, first login to victorio. Then
					issue the command <code>svn co svn://victorio.uit.no/boundcorpus
					</code>.
				</p>
			</section>

			<section>
				<title>Manually adding content</title>

				<p>
					If you have a file that you want to add to the corpus
					repository by hand you have to have a working copy of
					either the free or bound part of our corpus.
				</p>

				<ol>
					<li>
						If it is a freely distributable document, add it to the
						free part of our corpus. If not, add it to the bound part.
					</li>

					<li>
						Determine the main language: <code>eng, fin, nno,
						nob, sma, sme, smj, swe</code>, and then genre: <code>admin, bible,
						facta, ficti, laws, news</code>.
					</li>

					<li>
						Copy the file to the directory $working_copy/orig/$lang/$genre/. For
						example, a North Sámi document in genre "facta", copy the file to
						directory $working_copy/orig/sme/facta/ in your working copy. For
						the news genre, there are subdirectories for different sources of
						news, and for bible texts, there are subdirectories for ot and nt.
					</li>

					<li>
						Copy the file <code>$GTHOME/gt/script/XSL-template.xsl</code> to
						<code>$working_copy/orig/genre/$filename.xsl</code>. Update the metainformation by
						editing this file.
					</li>

					<li>
						Add and commit these files to the repository by either using the
						svn command line tools or your usual graphical interface to svn.
					</li>

				</ol>
			</section>

			<p>
				If you would like to have access our corpus, contact us at <a href="mailto:divvun@samediggi.no?subject=Corpus access">divvun@samediggi.no</a>
			</p>
		</section>

	</body>
</document>