<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Morphological disambiguation</title>

  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Morphological disambiguation</title>

      <p>The project uses Eckhard Bick and Tino Dideriksens <strong>vislcg3</strong>, a compiler for
      constraint grammar, a formalism originally developed by a.o. Fred Karlsson and Pasi
      Tapanainen at the University of Helsinki.</p>

      <ul>
        <li><a href="/tools/cg3-usage.html">How to use the disambiguator
        vislcg3</a></li>

        <li><a href="cgii-writing.html">How to write disambiguation
        files</a></li>
      </ul>

      <p>So far, we have a disambiguation file
      <code>sme-dis.rle</code>, for North Sámi, and a file
      <code>smj-dis.rle</code> for Lule Sámi. In addition to that, we
      are working on beta versions for Greenlandic and Faroese. The
      content of the North Saami file is documented <a
      href="/lang/sme/docu-sme-dis.html">here</a>. </p>

      <section>
        <title>Other versions of constraint grammar</title>

        <p>The philosophy behind constraint grammar is relatively simple, and
        the programming algorithms are found in several different version
        (the version we use at giellatekno is no. 5 on this list).</p>

        <ol>
          <li>The original CG formalism was developed by Fred Karlsson, at <a
          href="http://www.ling.helsinki.fi">Dept. of Linguistics in
          Helsinki</a></li>

          <li>Bart Jongejan's C++ version of the original CG</li>

          <li>A new version of CG, called CG-2, was developed by Pasi
          Tapanainen, cf. Tapanainen 1996. It is maintained by <a
          href="http://www.connexor.com">Connexor</a></li>

          <li>vislcg, an open source implementation of CG-2, at <a
          href="http://visl.hum.sdu.dk/visl/">http://visl.hum.sdu.dk/visl/</a>. This
          parser is available for download ad sourceforge, <a
          href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/vislcg/">here</a>.</li>

          <li>vislcg3, a new generation version ov the open source
          vislcg is currently being developed at <a
          href="http://visl.hum.sdu.dk/visl/">http://visl.hum.sdu.dk/visl/</a>.</li>

        </ol>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Other disambiguation tools</title>

        <section>
          <title>Grammar-based disambiguation tools</title>

          <ul>
            <li><a
            href="http://www.xrce.xerox.com/competencies/content-analysis/fssoft/docs/disamb-97/disamb97.html">disamb</a>,
            at Xerox</li>

            <li>FSIG (Finite-state intersection grammar), at <a
            href="http://www.ling.helsinki.fi">Dept. of Linguistics in
            Helsinki</a></li>

            <li>LFG and HPSG-based tools ??</li>
          </ul>

          <p>For various reasons, do not use these tools, but have chosen
          constraint grammar instead.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Statistically-based disambiguation tools</title>

          <p>This is the dominating approach to disambiguation. Here, we think
          the grammar-based approach is on the right track, and we thus do not
          use statistically-based tools. In the future it still may be
          relevant to have a look at what statixtically-based tools may
          achieve when applied on the top of grammar-based disambiguation
          tools, in order to resolve on statistical grounds such open cases
          that cannot be dealt with by grammatical tools alone.</p>

          <p>Thus, we should at some point start orientating ourself in the
          world of statistically-based disambiguation tools.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
       <title>Links to old documentation</title>
<p>These links are kept for reference, but not relevant for present usage.</p>
       <ul>
        <li><a href="/tools/cgii-usage.html">How to use the disambiguator
        vislcg</a></li>

        <li><a href="/tools/vislcg.html">Differences between vislcg and
        CG-2</a></li>
      </ul>

      </section>
      <section>
        <title>A disambiguation bibliography</title>

        <p>Forthcoming...</p>
      </section>

      
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
