<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>The list of foreign words</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>The list of foreign words</title>
      <p>Incoming text contains many foreign words. Used in isolation, as
spontanous loans, they should be delt with by a POS guesser. Text chunks in
foreign languages represent noise, though, and a good corpus should mark such
chunks with xml tags (&lt;foreign>&lt;/foreign>, etc.). While waiting for
that, and while developing our parser, we have a stoplist of foreign words.
The list was made in the following way:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Large lists of Norwegian, Swedish, Danish, Finnish and English words were sorted into one list, called <code>gt/script/old-foreign.txt</code>. The list was duplicated by an identical list with capital initial letter (using case.regex gave too long compilation time)</li>
        <li>The list was run through sme.fst, and the overlapping words (abonnere, adagio, Adam, addere, etc.) were removed.</li>
        <li>In addition, a file <code>gt/script/new-foreign.txt</code> was added to the cvs, containing Non-Saami words from our corpus files.</li>
        <li>Each of these files were turned into fst files. Then the union of the two files was made into one binary file, <em>foreign.fst</em>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>The compilation is included in the Makefile. The source files are in
        the <code>gt/script</code> catalogue, whereas the binary files are in
        the <code>gt/sme/bin</code> catalogue. Only <code>foreign.fst</code>
should be used, the two other ones are intermediate files.</p>
      <p>
        <code>foreign.fst</code> should be used as follows: When investigating
Saami words that the parser cannot cope with, foreign words are just noise.
They can be removed with this command line:</p>
      <source>cat text | preprocess ... | lookup -flags mbTT sme.fst | grep \?' |
cut -f1 | foreign.fst | grep '\?' | cut -f1 | ...
</source>
      <p>Now, only the words which are not recognised by the parser, and not part of the stop list, are included.</p>
      <p>The list of foreign words was cut in two because compilation time for the whole list is very long. The intention with the split is that <em>old-foreign.txt</em> should be left alone. All additional words should be added to the shorter <code>new-foreign.txt</code> file. If this file becomes too long, it may be transferred over to old-foreign.txt.</p>
      
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
