<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Language recognition using <code>pytextcat</code></title>

    <authors>
      <person email="sjur.moshagen@samediggi.no" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
    </authors>

    <abstract>To be able to identify sections within a document not in
    the main language, we need automatic language reqognition. We have
    installed an open-source package that performs such a task, and
    this page documents its usage and origin (cf. the Source section
    at the bottom of the page for background info)..</abstract>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Usage</title>
      
      <p>The primary use of this tool is via the corpus conversion
      tool <a href="corpus_conversion_tech.html">convert2xml</a>. When
      you use convert2xml in order to turn original corpus documents
      into text for processing, the language recogniser is
      automatically put into use. You may also use it as a standalone
      program. See the help text by writing <code>pytextcat proc
      -h</code></p>

      <p>Typical usage as a standalone program will be something like:</p>

      <source>pytextcat proc $GTHOME/tools/CorpusTools/corpustools/lm &lt; testfile.txt</source>

      <p><code>pytextcat</code> will return the name (the ISO code, to
      be exact) of the language(s) the script believes the text to be
      in.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adding a new recognizable language</title>

      <p>The pytextcat reference files are stored in $GTHOME/tools/CorpusTools/corpustools/.</p>

<p>Adding a new language to be recognized requires a suitable training
      corpus to be built. This is most easily done with the accompanying tool
      <code>random_lines</code>:</p>

      <source>random_lines &lt; some-text-file &gt; ShortTexts/language-name.txt</source>

      <p>This commando extracts random lines of text from the input
      file, and stores them in the output file. It also cleans the
      file a bit. The file created is used to build a language model
      like this (assuming you stand in
      $GTHOME/tools/CorpusTools/corpustools/):</p>

      <source>cat someinput | pytextcat complm &gt; lm/language-iso-code.lm</source>
      <source>cat someinput | pytextcat compwm &gt; lm/language-iso-code.wm</source>

      <p>After this, the language recognition tool <code>pytextcat</code> is
      ready for use with another language as shown in the previous
      section.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Source</title>

      <p>The home page of the original perl-based package TextCat is found at several locations.</p>
 <ul>
<li>
 <a
      href="https://www.let.rug.nl/vannoord/TextCat/">The original page at University of
      Groningen</a>, with the source code. The package is lisenced under a GPL license — see the home
      page for details — and it is developed by Gertjan van Noord</li>
<li><a href="https://gtsvn.uit.no/langtech/trunk/tools/">The source code is also available in the Giellatekno repository (TODO: Fix)</a></li>
</ul>
      <p>. The Groningen home  page also
      includes links to a background article, a list of supported languages
      coming with the tools, and also a list of competitors. Here's also
      another <a
      href="http://odur.let.rug.nl/~vannoord/TextCat/Demo/textcat.html">link
      to a demo page</a>, with e-mail address of the author.</p>

      <p>The python implementation <code>pytextcat</code> we use here was written by Kevin Unhammer.</p>
      
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
