<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en" >
    <header>
        <title>General information </title>
        <authors>
            <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
        </authors>
    </header>
    <body>
        <section id="General_information_for_new_users" >

            <title>General information for new users</title>

            <p>
                Here you will find the technical documentation of the
                <em>Sámi language technology project</em> (also called
                <em>Giellatekno</em>), and its twin project
                <em>Divvun</em> (making Sámi spellers), both conducted
                at the University of Tromsø.
            </p>
            <p>
                In the thin menu line above you see: 
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    The <em>Project</em> tab that gives some general information about both projects.
                </li>
                <li>
                    The <em>Meetings</em> tab that contains the minutes of our meetings, both from our weekly (virtual) meetings and from the other meetings we have held during the project
                </li>
                <li>
                    The <em>Infrastructure</em> tab that contains information on how to set up your computer to be able to use the tools and programs to be able to work with our source code and documentation on your own machine.
                </li>
                <li>
                    The <em>Language</em> tab that is divided into one subpart for each language treated. It contains detailed documentation on the source files for each language.
                </li>
                <li>
                    The <em>Linguistics</em> tab that contains language-independent documentation on how to
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            convert texts to our corpus format
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            preprocess files
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            use the morphologial parsers
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            do disambiguation of Saami texts
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>The <em>MT</em> tab documents our work on machine translation (together with <a href="http://wiki.apertium.org">Apertium</a>)</li>
                <li>The <em>Ped</em> tab documents our pedagogical project</li>
                <li>The <em>Tools</em> tab that gives an introduction on how to use the tools that are described under the Infrastructure tab</li>
                <li>The <em>Dicts</em> tab links to documentation on our dictionary word.</li>
                <li>The <em>Bugzilla</em> tab links directly to our bug database.</li>
            </ul>
            
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Documentation and source code</title>
            <p>
                The source code and the documentation of these projects are under <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revision_control" >version control</a>, using the program <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subversion_%28software%29" >svn</a>.
            </p>
            <p>svn makes it possible for everyone to fetch our source code and documentation to their own machine, and tinker with it in peace and quiet. There are several ways of fetching the files to your own machine.</p>
            <ul>
                <li>If you just want to browse through the file, or download them one by one, you may browse the <a href="https://victorio.uit.no/langtech/trunk/">source file directory</a></li>
                <li>Those who have an account on our svn server can both fetch files (called check out) and write back changed files (called check in) on this server. <a href="/doc/tools/docu-svn-user.html" >(Instructions)</a></li>
                <li>Others who don't have an account at our server can only fetch files and don't write back changes. <a href="/doc/infra/anonymous-svn.html" >(Instructions)</a>.</li>
            <li>If you want to compile our source code you must have one of these two compilers for finite state automata (at the moment we recommend the Xerox compilers, our HFST setup is still not stable):
<ul>
<li>the <a href="http://www.xrce.xerox.com/competencies/content-analysis/fst/">Xerox finite state tools</a>. This is proprietary software which is bundled with the book <a href="http://csli-publications.stanford.edu/site/1575864347.html">Finite State Morphology</a>.</li>
<li>Helsinki Finite State Transdocer, HFST. HFST is open software.</li>
</ul></li>
            <li> For syntactic disambiguation, you will need the <a href="tools/docu-vislcg3.html">vislcg3 program</a>.</li>
<li><a href="docu-directorystructure.html">Directory structure for the source code</a></li>
            </ul>
            
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
