<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Anonymous SVN</title>

    <authors>
      <person email="boerre.gaup@samediggi.no" name="Børre Gaup" />

      <person email="sjur.moshagen@samediggi.no" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <note>
      The source code and the documentation is distributed under the 
      GPL-license. You will find the license text in xtdoc/LISENS.txt
      and gt/LISENS.txt.
    </note>
    <note>Preparation and Check-out you will only have to do once</note>

    <section>
      <title>Preparation</title>

      <p>Anyone can download the source code via anonymous SVN, but will not
      be able to contribute with modifications.</p>

      <p>To get the files, do the following: Open a terminal and use the following command to fetch the files:</p>

      <source>svn co https://victorio.uit.no/langtech/trunk</source>

      <p>The files will then be copied to your machine (you will see a row of filenames, preceeded by the letter A).</p>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Building, compiling and running</title>

      <p>When everything is checked out and residing on your computer, you
      probably want to compile and run our linguistic analysers. For this you
      need to install the required tools. They are:</p>

      <ul>
        <li><strong>Xerox morphological transducer tools</strong>, for
        morphological analysis. This is proprietary software, and not
        available for download, but it is included with the book Finite State
        Morphology by <a
        href="http://www.xrce.xerox.com/people/beesley/home.html">Kenneth R.
        Beesley</a> and <a
        href="http://www2.parc.com/istl/members/karttune/">Lauri
        Karttunen</a>. <a
        href="http://csli-publications.stanford.edu/site/1575864347.html">The
        book</a> has its own <a href="http://www.fsmbook.com/">home page</a>.
        Unfortunately we do not have an open source alternative for compiling
        our morphological analysers, basically because there are none
        compatible with our source, and almost none able to handle Sámi in a
        decent way. One possible open-source alternative would be <a
        href="http://www.ims.uni-stuttgart.de/projekte/gramotron/SOFTWARE/SFST.html">SFST</a>,
        but it would require major reworking of our lexicons, and a lot of
        other work as well.</li>

        <li><strong>vislcg</strong>, for disambiguation. This is open source,
        but has no documentation accompanying the software (there are
        references to external/printed documentation). We have written <a href ="/doc/tools/docu-vislcg3.html">instructions on how to compile and and use vislcg3</a>.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Other tools (perl scripts, shell scripts, etc.) should have been
      included in the SVN check-out, but might require some environment setups
      (PATHs etc). See our <a href="workenvironment.html">technical
      documentation</a> and the subsection in the corresponding menu.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Reading the documentation off-line</title>

      <p>The full documentation is available online on <a
      href="http://www.divvun.no/">divvun.no</a>, but if you want to read the
      documentation off-line, you are best off installing and running
      <strong><a href="http://forrest.apache.org/">Forrest</a></strong>. You 
      will find it at 
      <a href="http://divvun.no/static_files/divvun_forrest.tar.bz2">our
       server</a>.</p>

      <p>We have made a <a href="forrest-howto.html">document</a> on how to 
      install and use forrest, follow the instructions there on how to use 
      forrest on your private machine</p>
      
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sending feedback and patches</title>

      <p>If you have improvements to our code, be it linguistic corrections,
      C-code bug fixes, documentation enhancements or whatever, we would
      welcome your contribution. Please make a cvs diff, gzip it, and send it
      <a href="mailto:divvun@samediggi.no">to us</a>.</p>

      <warning>This e-mail address may change in the future!</warning>

      <section>
        <title>Interactive feedback and discussions</title>

        <p>The whole team is available on AIM, and we frequently keep
        discussions through our favourite AIM client(s). Our AIM addresses can
        be found on our <a href="/doc/admin/people.html">contact page</a>.</p>

        <p>We also use <a
        href="http://www.codingmonkeys.de/subethaedit/">SubEthaEdit</a> (SEE)
        a lot to do collaborative development, but SEE is Mac only, and
        commercial (version 2.2 is available for free for non-commercial
        purposes). A cross-platform alternative is <a
        href="http://gobby.0x539.de/">Gobby</a> (please see the <a
        href="http://darcs.0x539.de/trac/obby/cgi-bin/trac.cgi/wiki/InstallationGuide">installation
        notes</a>, especially Mac users - the Mac version only installs
        through <a href="http://darwinports.opendarwin.org/">DarwinPorts</a>).
        Try it, or SEE - realtime collaborative development is both very fun
        and productive, and creates a whole new feeling of working together,
        even when sitting in different countries! Much of what we have done
        would have taken 10 x the time, or not been possible at all without
        SEE.</p>

        <p>If you have questions or problems, either e-mail us, or start a
        chat. Further investigation can be done collaboratively and
        interactively using SEE or Gobby. If you are using a Mac with a recent
        OS version (10.4.x, aka Tiger), you can even invite us to (group)
        voice or video chats using <a
        href="http://www.apple.com/ichat/">iChat</a>. Non-group voice and
        video chats should also work with earlier versions of MacOS, as well as
        with a recent version of the AIM client for Windows (we haven't tried
        voice or video chats with Windows users).</p>
      </section>
    </section>

<!--     <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by $Author$</p> -->
  </body>
</document>
