<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Sámi keyboard</title>

    <authors>
      <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Sámi keyboard</title>

      <p>Sámi keyboard and letters come ready installed on Windows, Mac and Linux.</p>

          <section>
        <title>Windows</title>

        <p>Activating the Sámi keyboard in Windows XP (Vista is in principle identical)</p>
        <ul>
        <li>The Start menu → Control panel → (Date, time, language...) → Settings for region and language</li>
        <li>In this window, press the pane <em>Language</em>, and the button <em>Details</em></li>
        <li>Press <em>Add</em> and under the menu <em>Input language</em> choose <em>North Sami (Norway)</em>.</li>
        <li>For <em>Keyboard setting/IME</em>, choose <em>Sami, extended Norway</em>. (NB! Do NOT choose "Norwegian with Sami", this is the wrong keyboard.)</li>
        <li>For the button <em>Language box</em>, tick for <em>Show the language box on the desktop</em></li>
        <li>Press <em>OK</em> on all OK-buttons on your way out of the panel, and close the Control panel.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>In order to change between Norwegian and Sámi keyboard, keep the left Alt key down and press the Shift key at the same time. The indicator (a small blue square) down right on the taskbar changes between <em>en</em> (English keyboard) and <em>sm</em> (Sami keyboard).</p>
        
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Macintosh</title>

        <ul>
        <li>Via <em>The Apple menu</em> in the upper left corner choose <em>System preferences</em> and <em>International</em>.</li>
        <li>Choose the pane <em>Input menu</em>, and tick the box for <em>Northern Sami</em> on the list.</li>
        <li>Choose <em>Show input menu in menu bar</em></li>.
        <li>Note the <em>Input menu shortcuts</em>, they may be changed via the <em>Keyboard shortcuts...</em></li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>You may now change between your keyboards by pressing the keyboard shortcut (standard is <em>⌘Space</em>), or by clicking the flag in the upper right corner (English/Sami)</p> 
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Linux</title>

        <p>Setup on Linux works in the same way as for Windows og Mac. Look for the Control panel.</p>
      </section>
      
            <section>
        <title>Placement of the Sámi keys on the keyboard</title>

        <p>The Sámi letters are found on the same position for all operative systems.</p>
        <table>
<!--	  <tr><td>Letter</td><td>Key</td><td>Letter</td><td>Key</td><td>Letter</td><td>Key</td><td>Letter</td><td>Key</td></tr>
-->
        <tr><td>á on the q key</td><td>č on the x key</td><td>đ on the \ key</td><td>ŋ on the ] key</td></tr>
        <tr><td>š on the w key</td><td>ŧ on the y key</td><td>ž on the ` key</td></tr>
        </table>
	<p>Here is a picture of the North Sámi keyboard:</p>
        <p><img src="sme-key.png" /></p>
      </section>

      <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date: 2008-11-05 18:52:54 +0100 (ons, 05 nov 2008) $, by
      $Author: boerre $</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>