<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Localisation</title>

  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Localisation</title>

      <p>All our projects are run in UTF-8, since the spring of 2005.</p>

      <p>There is one exception, and it is not in-house: The Oslo web interface Glossa
      handles only 8-bit code tables. Our texts at glossa are coded in 
      <a href="http://www.hum.uit.no/a/trond/197.jpg">ISO-IR 197</a>.</p>

      <section>
        <title>North Saami</title>

        <p>The North Saami parser is localised with UTF-8, as it should be.
        In our web interface there is a filter to let users feed in c1, d1, s1, etc,
         instead of the correct Saami letters. Output to the user is in UTF-8.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Lule Saami </title>

        <p>Lule Saami can adequately be represented in 8-bit format, by Latin 1
        (Lule Saami files can use <em>ñ</em> for n-acute). In order to have
        only one localisation interface for the languages we work on, Lule
        Saami has been moved to UTF-8 as well. There is a script,
        <code>spell-relax.regex</code>, which makes it possible to use both ñ,
        ń and ŋ.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>South Saami</title>

        <p>Also South Saami can be represented in 8-bit format, by Latin 1,
        but just as for Lule Saami, it is stored in UTF-8. The script 
        <code>spell-relax.regex</code> is used for South Saami as well, but 
        with a slightly different purpose: It is used to accept the wide-spread
        sloppy use of <em>i</em> for <em>ï</em>.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Inari, Skolt and Kildin Saami</title>

        <p>Inari Saami, Skolt and Kildin Saami are repesented in Unicode.</p>
      </section>


      <section>
        <title>Our other languages</title>

        <p>All our other languages are in UTF-8 as well.</p>
        <p>Note that for Iñupiaq, we do <em>not</em> use the wide-spread 8-bit
        <em>Interactive IñupiaQ Dictionary</em> encoding, as it has placed the Iñupiaq
        characters in the ASCII area. There is a converter on the Iñupiaq page.</p>
      </section>
      
    </section>
  </body>
</document>