<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
                          "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en"> 
    <header> 
        <title>Forrest i18n effort</title>

	<authors>
	  <person email="sjur.moshagen@samediggi.no" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
	  <person email="tomi.pieski@samediggi.no" name="Tomi Pieski" />
	  <person email="borre.gaup@samediggi.no" name="Børre Gaup" />
	</authors>

    </header> 
    <body> 
        <section>
            <title>Forrest i18n subproject</title>
            <p>We need to get Forrest i18n to work to present users and the 
            general audience with a decent and working language menu that
            reflects the list of available languages.</p>

            <p>Tasks:</p>
            <ul>
              <li>Define the wanted behaviour</li>
              <li>Collect the pieces available presently in Forrest, and test 
                  the present implementation</li>
              <li>Identify the problems with the existing version</li>
              <li>Make our own changes to get Forrest to behave like we want it
                  to</li>
              <li>Present the solution to the Forrest list (dev), and hopefully
                  get it accepted.
                  <note>All of us should start subscribing to
                  the Forrest dev list!</note></li>
              <li>Install a new version of the Forrest-doc on divvun.no.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The wanted behaviour</title>
            <p>Have a look at
               <a href="http://www.risten.no/exist/risten">risten.no</a>.
               The available languages are listed to the top right, and one can 
               change the interface language by clicking the links (which is 
               just the server address augmented with ?locale=xx, see next 
               section).</p>
            <p>For a document centric site, we would like to have the language 
               menu generated dynamically, and reflect the available 
               language versions for the document in question. For pages
               available in only one language, the lang menu should reflect
               this by displaying the language of the document.
            </p>
            <p>In cases where the browser requests an unavailable locale or no
               locale, Forrest should return the default locale as specified
               in either forrest.properties or skinconf.xml. That is, a request
               for index.html should be turned into a request for index_se.xml
               if <code>default-lang=se</code>.
            </p>
            <p>The language (override) menu should be configurable from skinconf.xml,
               with the default rendering being a horizontal list along the
               top of the page. Both appearance (list, menu) and location (top,
               tabs, other location?) should be configurable independently.
            </p>
            <p>The menu texts and all tabs and other text elements outside the
               content proper should be translated into the specified locale
               using standard Cocoon/Forrest translation dictionaries. If a
               locale is available for the document itself, but not all text
               elements to be translated, the fallback (and eventually the
               default) language should be used.
            </p>
            <p>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Current situation (Forrest svn version as of May 25, 2005)
               </title>
            <p>A very <a
               href="http://casa.che-che.com/blog/2005/05/10/internalization-a-site-using-forrest-07-dev/"
               >recent blog</a> describes the steps to turn on and utilise
               i18n. Unfortunately, it doesn't completely match what we have
               found - read on (what is good is that Forrest now degrades
               gracefully, without a 404 error).</p>
            <p>Forrest uses its internationalisation features when they are
               enabled in forrest.properties: <code>project.i18n=true</code></p>
            <p>It is able to specify the wanted locale using 
               <code>http://localhost:8888/index.html?locale=se</code>, or by 
               letting the browser decide the locale. Forrest then chooses 
               index_se.xml, and falls back to the default language when the
               locale isn't found.</p>
            <p>If the tabs_se.xml and site_se.xml files exist in 
               <code>translation</code> directory, the menus and tabs are 
               translated as well, but only if the requested locale is specified
               by the browser.</p>
            <p>What is still missing from the present Forrest version is a
               language override menu. Also, the menus and tabs aren't
               translated if a locale is specified within a URL (as <code>
               index.html?locale=sme</code>).</p>
            <p>Problem summary:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Forrest menu translation works only if locale is coming
                    from browser - the same might be the case with the tabs,
                    but that is not yet tested</li>
                <li>Document locale is disregarded if locale is taken from
                    browser</li>
                <li>There's no documented way of specifying the default
                    language, or generating the language override menu from
                    the content of whatever.xml (without any locale in the
                    filename) to make the default language listed among all
                    languages</li>
                <li>No language override menu is generated</li>
                <li>Since no language override menu is generated, our requests
                    for override menu configuration can not be evaluated
                    further</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
	    <p>Last modified: $Date$, by $Author$</p>
    </body>
</document>
