<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
                          "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en"> 
    <header> 
        <title>Lucene and Local Search Overview</title>

	<authors>
	  <person email="sjur.moshagen@samediggi.no" name="Sjur N. Moshagen" />
	</authors>

    </header> 
    <body> 

      <warning>This information is useful only to project members and others
      having access to our cvs repository. Do not try to update or create
      a lucene index on the public site. It won't do any harm, but it won't
      do any good either. The public site is fully searchable with Google.
      </warning>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>To help us use the built-in search engine, and make it easier to
      remember the existence of it, the basic links are now available in the
      menu when opening the Tech Doc tab.</p>

      <p>The index must be regenerated with regular intervals or after major
      changes to the documentation, to stay up-to-date. (Actually, to be
      completely up to date, it has to be regenerated each time there is a
      change to any document within the <code>gt/doc/</code> hierarchy.)</p>

      <p>It might be a good idea to let forrest be running all the time -
      any changes to the documentation will be picked up automatically as
      you update from cvs (with the exception of changes to
      <code>site-frags.xml</code> and <code>tabs-frags.xml</code> - you need
      to <code>touch</code> the corresponding main files <code>site.xml</code>
      and <code>tabs.xml</code> for the changes to be picked up).</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Searching your local Forrest</title>
 
      <p>Our public home page is searched with Google, but you can still search
      the local copy of Forrest with the latest document updates. The default
      search box is now Lucene based. The only thing to remember is to
      update the Lucene index:</p>

      <p><a href="http://localhost:8888/lucene-update.html">
      http://localhost:8888/lucene-update.html</a> — or use the menu entry to
      the left.</p>

      <warning>The above link, as well as the menu entry, will only work for
      local instances of Forrest when
      started with default settings using the command <code>forrest run</code>.
      </warning>

      <p>After the index has been (re)generated, just type in your search
      string in the search box at the top of every page, and press Enter.</p>

    </section>

      
         by $Author$</p>
    </body>
</document>
