<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Connecting to the main computer <em>victorio</em></title>
    <authors>
      <person email="trond.trosterud" name="Trond Trosterud" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Should I work on victorio or on my own machine?</title>

      <p>If you have one of the project macs set up for you, you have all
      tools on your own machine, and you may as well work offline. In that
      case, you use the <a href="../tools/docu-svn-user.xml">CVL program</a>
      to get the latest versions of the files from the central computer
      victorio, and thereafter you use the tools on your own machine, as
      described in the Tools section.</p>

      <p>If you do not have the Xerox tools installed on your local machine,
      you must be connected to victorio in order to compile the program, and in
      order to use it.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Connecting to victorio</title>

        <p>All platforms will need a few initial tweaks to make them handle
        the Sámi characters, but if you already write Sámi on your computer it
        may be that it is set up correctly already. See the <a
        href="docu-localisation.xml">localisation page</a> if you have
        problems.</p>

        <section>
          <title>Mac users</title>

          <p>Mac users using Mac OS X have built-in SSH and a terminal
          application. Just open the terminal, and type <code>ssh
          username@victorio.uit.no</code> at your prompt (where 'username' is
          your own user name at victorio).</p>

          <p>Mac users using OS 9 or earlier may access victorio via a program
          called NiftyTelnet (downloadable from the <a
          href="http://asg.web.cmu.edu/andrew2/dist/niftytelnet.html">NiftyTelnet
          Homepage</a>). But note that OS 9 does not handle Unicode</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Linux users</title>

          <p>Linux users use the same ssh command as was described for Mac OSX
          above.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Windows users</title>

          <p>Windows users may e.g. use <a
          href="../tools/docu-putty.xml">putty.exe</a>. <strong>Remember to
          connect via ssh</strong>, not via Telnet. After we switched to Sámi
          letters internally, putty is not an ideal solution, since it for
          some reason is not able to write the letter č (all other Sámi
          letters work). (<strong>TODO</strong>: Check other terminal programs
          for Windows)</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Reading the documentation</title>

        <p>In order to read the documentation offline, you must have a program
        called forrest installed (se separate forrest documentation). </p>

        <p>If you don't have forrest installed on your own machine, you may
        read the documentation online, on victorio (NB! forrest is not
        installed there yet).</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Editing files</title>

        <p>Do <strong>not</strong> use Microsoft Word or any other word
        processor. Word processors and text editors are two different things.
        Word processors are made to let the text look nice, text editors are
        made to edit text. In this project, we edit text. Word processors add
        secret code that makes text nice, but this code only crashes our
        programs and hampers our work.</p>

        <p>There is separate documentation on editors on the <a
        href="../tools/tools.xml">Tools page</a>.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Downloading files</title>

        <p>For downloading files on <strong>Windows</strong>, see the
        description on the <a href="../tools/docu-putty.xml">putty page</a>.</p>

        <p>For downloading files on <strong>Linux and Mac</strong>, use the
        scp procedure. On the command line on your local Linux PC, write
        (supposing your user name is trond) and you want to copy this file to
        your local machine and call it off.xml:</p>

        <p>scp trond@victorio.uit.no:gt/doc/offline.xml off.xml</p>

        <p>In order to copy files to victorio, just switch the arguments.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Troubleshooting</title>

        <p>What may go wrong?</p>

        <dl>
          <dt>I connect via putty or NiftyTelnet, but do not get any
          "username" prompt</dt>

          <dd><ol>
              <li>There may be a firewall active. Contact your system
              administrator</li>

              <li>Perhaps you forgot to use SSH instead of Telnet</li>

              <li>Perhaps you are not on the internet</li>
            </ol></dd>

          <dt>More trouble..?</dt>

          <dd>..must be</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by $Author$</p>

    </section>
  </body>
</document>