<html xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en">
   <head>
      <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8">
      <title>Setup subversion client programs</title>
   </head>
   <body>
      <p>This document describes how to setup the svn client programs on Mac, Windows and Linux</p>
      <h1>Mac</h1>
      <p>Download a suitable graphical client: <a href="http://versionsapp.com/">Versions.app</a>, <a href="http://www.lachoseinteractive.net/en/community/subversion/svnx/download/">svnX program</a> or <a href="http://www.rapidsvn.org/index.php/Documentation#Mac_OS.2FX">RapidSVN</a>. The <a href="http://homepage.mac.com/martinott/Subversion-1.4.4.pkg.zip">commandline client program</a> is part of the
         system if you have installed the developer tools (XCode - included on your installation
         CD). You may still want
         to install a newer version if you are using MacOS X 10.4 (Tiger) or 10.5 (Leopard),
         though. MacOS X 10.6 (Snow
         Leopard) has a pretty recent version of the command-line tool.
      </p>
      <h1>Windows</h1>
      <p>Download and install <a href="http://tortoisesvn.net/downloads">TortoiseSVN</a> or <a href="http://www.rapidsvn.org/index.php/Documentation#Windows">RapidSVN</a>.
      </p>
      <h1>Linux</h1>
      <p>To install the commandline version of subversion, issue either the command <code>sudo apt-get install
            subversion</code> or <code>sudo yum install subversion</code></p>
      <p>There are at least two alternatives if you want a graphical user interface, kdesvn
         and rapidsvn. Under
         Debian/Ubuntu: <code>sudo apt-get install rapidsvn</code> or <code>sudo apt-get install rapidsvn</code></p>
      <p>Under Fedora/CentOS/Red Hat <code>sudo yum install rapidsvn</code> or <code>sudo yum install
            kdesvn</code>.
      </p>
      <h1>CVS Infrastructure</h1>
      <note>We use svn now</note>
      <p>To make CVS commit mailings work, one has to edit the file
         <code>CVSROOT/loginfo</code>. It should already be set-up correctly,
         but for the sake of documentation and understanding, it is repeated
         here:
      </p>
      <pre xml:space="preserve">
^gt          mail -s %s samicvs
^kt          mail -s %s samicvs
^st          mail -s %s samicvs
^termdb      mail -s %s samicvs
^xtdoc       mail -s %s samicvs
</pre>
      <p>After that file is created/modified, we need to ensure that the
         mail alias <code>samicvs</code> is working by editing
         <code>/etc/aliases</code>. At the bottom of that file, that alias is
         defined as follows:
      </p>
      <pre xml:space="preserve">samicvs: trond,boerre,sjur,tomi</pre>
      <p>More names can and will be added when we see that it works, and all
         has been informed. When the alias is changed, or a new one created,
         one has to run
         the command <code>newaliases</code> as root or superuser. Then
         all mail to the alias samicvs will be forwarded to the local
         users listed.
      </p>
      <p>Finally, to forward your e-mail to your regular account, create the
         following file in your home directory: <code>.forward</code>,
         containing only the mail address of the account you want to receive
         commit mails on. Remember to add a linefeed at the end (that is, type
         return). For this forward file to work correctly, it has to have
         correct permissions, which you ensure with the following command:
      </p>
      <pre xml:space="preserve">chmod 644 .forward</pre>
      <p>That's it! Now we should all get an e-mail each time someone commits
         a file. Hint: as the amount of e-mail this generates can be quite
         high, it is advisable to create a filter in your mail application
         that will put all cvs and Bugzilla e-mails in a dedicated folder.
      </p>
   </body>
</html>