<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
                          "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en"> 
    <header> 
        <title>OpenOffice.org Hyphenation Technical Documentation</title>
    </header> 
    <body> 
	  
	  <p>An OpenOffice.org hyphenator was not a fixed part of the original plan,
	  rather it was indicated as an optional addition. Part of the reason for
	  this was that at the time I could not find information on how to implement
	  it. Now the information is there (or: we have found it), and we'll try to
	  add Sámi hyphenation after we have the OOo speller in place. Relevant
	  links are:</p>
	  <ul>
	    <li><a href="http://www.openoffice.org/lingucomponent/hyphenator.html"
	       >OOo Lingucomponent, hyphenation</a>, includes a brief how-to</li>
	    <li><a href="http://wiki.services.openoffice.org/wiki/Dictionaries">OOo
	       Dictionary Wiki</a>, with link to hyphenation dictionary creation
	       tool</li>
	    <li>A copy of the <a href="userguide-p.pdf">user manual</a> for <a
	       href="http://www.fi.muni.cz/~xantos/patlib/">OPatGen</a> (see below)
	       is available.</li>
	  </ul>

	  <p>Basically, the task of creating TeX hyphenation pattern files consis
	  of the following steps:</p>
	  <ol>
	    <li>print the lower side of a hyphenated, normative transducer to
	       produce a correctly hyphenated word list</li>
	    <li>run that list through OPatGen (see PatLib above) and associated
	       scripts - see the user documentation above</li>
	    <li>test the result</li>
	  </ol>
	  <p>We need to install OPatGen first, which in turn needs
	  <code>cweave</code>.</p>

	  <p>Steps to install <code>cweave</code>:</p>
	  <source>sudo port install texlive-bin-extra</source>
	  
	  <p>Steps to install <code>opatgen</code> (we have a local copy of the
	  code):</p>
	  <ol>
	     <li><code>cd $GTHOME/tools/patlib</code></li>
	     <li><p><code>make</code><br/>
	       <strong>NB!</strong> At the moment the C compilation is broken,
	       because the code rely on a number of old, non-conformant coding
	       practices. <code>gcc 2.95</code> is required, which is not available
	       on any modern systems anymore. We either need to upgrade the code,
	       or find an alternative solution.</p>
	       <p>We have successfully modernised the code of
	       <code>tools/dic2traskelet.C</code> (a helper tool), but the C code
	       of the main application is a bit more complex to cover.</p>
	     </li>
	     <li><code></code></li>
	     <li><code></code></li>
	  </ol>

    </body>
</document>
