<html xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en">
   <head>
      <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8">
      <title>Project Management</title>
      <version major="0" minor="1" tag="$Id$">First
         draft
      </version>
      <authors>
         <person email="sjur.moshagen@samediggi.no" name="Sjur N. Moshagen"></person>
      </authors>
      <abstract>An overview of methods, tools and processes for managing
         software development projects. Language technology projects are
         essentially software development, and proofing tools development even more
         so.
      </abstract>
   </head>
   <body>
      <h1>Links</h1>
      <p>Initially, this is just a collection of links to useful internal and
         external documents:
      </p>
      <ul>
         <li>An <a href="projmantools.html">overview and evaluation</a> of
            software tools to support project management
         </li>
         <li>A <a href="http://www.dixite.com/pages/pdf/sposs_v1.0.pdf">document
               describing the whole software production process</a> using OSS (Open
            Source Software) - from <a href="http://www.dixite.com/docs/spposs/">Dixite.com</a></li>
      </ul>
      <h1>Development process</h1>
      <p>The main highlights from the Dixite document is the following process
         and related tools:
      </p>
      <ol>
         <li>Planning - <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Apache
               Maven</a></li>
         <li>Requirement Analysis and Specification - <a href="http://argouml.tigris.org/">ArgoUML</a>, CVS and DocBook (XML)
            as well as LaTeX for (version control of) documentation
         </li>
         <li>Design and Specification - Dixite uses <a href="http://argouml.tigris.org/">ArgoUML</a>, and <a href="http://www.xfig.org/">Xfig</a> (runs under X11) for higher level
            graphing, I suggest we use <a href="http://www.omnigroup.com/applications/omnigraffle/">OmniGraffle</a>
            for graphing purposes.
         </li>
         <li>Implementation and Unit Testing - a plethora of software,
            depending on the tasks at hand.
         </li>
         <li>System Integration and Testing - <a href="http://www.junit.org/index.htm">JUnit</a> and <a href="http://www.bugzilla.org/">Bugzilla</a></li>
         <li>Delivery and Maintenance - <a href="http://www.bugzilla.org/">Bugzilla</a></li>
      </ol>
      <p>We have so far not had any real development process, only doing bits
         of 4 and 5 without support from a real plan, no design, no
         specifications, and testing only of the inflection of the linguistic
         models (we have very recently added the facilities to test two-level
         rules, but that isn't put to much use yet).
      </p>
      <h1>Software we have</h1>
      <p>We are already using several of the tools listed by Dixite (CVS,
         Bugzilla, XML-based documentation). If we set up a development process
         similar to the above, with software used specified, we arrive at the
         following:
      </p>
      <ol>
         <li>Planning – [nothing really, that is, MS Word and Excel] see the <a href="projmantools.html">list of candidates</a> for more info
         </li>
         <li>Requirement Analysis and Specification – Forrest</li>
         <li>Design and Specification – Forrest</li>
         <li>Implementation and Testing –</li>
         <li>System Integration and Testing –</li>
         <li>Delivery and Maintenance – Forrest, CVS, Bugzilla</li>
      </ol>
      <h1>Suggested additions to our tool chest</h1>
      <p>For the missing parts I suggest we look more into the following
         packages:
      </p>
      <ul>
         <li><a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Apache Maven</a> – project
            management (but cf also the list of <a href="projmantools.html">commercial project management tools</a>)
            <ul>
               <li>Maven is now officially dead - see the home page. The most
                  likely candidate now is the commercial, Mac-only tool Merlin (<a href="/admin/projmantools.html#Merlin+1.3.6">more
                     info</a>).
               </li>
            </ul>
         </li>
         <li><a href="http://argouml.tigris.org/">ArgoUML</a> – design,
            specifications and use cases.
         </li>
         <li><a href="http://www.junit.org/index.htm">JUnit</a> derivatives for
            our purposes (= more systematic testing) - if we can't find something
            suitable, we need to look into what we can do ourselves to ensure
            proper regression testing and testing routines in general. The present
            testing system is too random, and doesn't automatize the process of
            checking against earlier bugfixes when new bugs have been fixed.
         </li>
         <li><a href="http://www.omnigroup.com/applications/omnigraffle/">OmniGraffle</a>
            — we are already using it for small-scale drawing, I suggest we buy
            full licenses for this one
         </li>
         <li>OmniOutline — it is included with our computers, and is a good
            tool for developing plans, and all sorts of outline activities more
            advanced than what can be done with the wiki format
         </li>
      </ul>
      <h1>Updated software list</h1>
      <p>After having investigated several tools and options, the following
         set of tools is what we will use for the main phases of our project
         (editors of different types, like SubEthaEdit, emacs and XXE, are not
         listed, just assumed):
      </p>
      <ol>
         <li>Planning – Merlin, OmniOutline, OmniGraffle, Forrest</li>
         <li>Requirement Analysis and Specification – Forrest, Merlin, ArgoUML,
            OmniOG
         </li>
         <li>Design and Specifiation – Forrest, Merlin, ArgoUML, OmniOG</li>
         <li>Implementation and Testing – Xerox, home-made testing routines,
            Bugzilla
         </li>
         <li>System Integration and Testing – Bugzilla, software from
            integrators, home-made testing routines
         </li>
         <li>Delivery and Maintenance – Forrest, CVS, Bugzilla</li>
      </ol>
      <p>What is still open, is how to test Aspell and similar engines, as
         well as the hyphenation. For Aspell and other Unix spellers, a lot of
         testing can be automated, and the routines needs to be worked out. All
         testing needs to be formalised, and the results should be collected
         systematically, preferably automatically, and stored and processed to
         monitor the development of the tools.
      </p>
      <h1>UML References</h1>
      <p>UML is news to most of us, so here's a list of references.</p>
      <ul>
         <li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unified_Modeling_Language">UML in
               WikiPedia</a></li>
         <li>What is a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Use_case">Use
               Case</a>?
         </li>
         <li><a href="http://www.methodsandtools.com/archive/archive.php?id=24">Understanding
               Use Case Modelling</a></li>
         <li><a href="http://www.methodsandtools.com/archive/archive.php?id=8">Precise
               Use Cases</a></li>
         <li>ArgoUML <a href="http://argouml.tigris.org/documentation/defaulthtml/manual/">User
               Manual</a></li>
      </ul>
   </body>
</html>