<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
   <header>
      <title>Linguistic modelling: Publications and presentations</title>
   </header>
   <body>
<ul>
      <li>Snoek, Conor; Thunder, Dorothy; Lõo, Kaidi; Arppe, Antti; Lachler, Jordan; Moshagen, Sjur; Trosterud, Trond. <a href="http://acl2014.org/acl2014/W14-22/pdf/W14-2205.pdf">Modeling the Noun Morphology of Plains Cree. </a> Proceedings of the 2014 Workshop on the Use of Computational Methods in the Study of Endangered Languages, p. 34–42.</li>
      <li>Moshagen, Sjur; Ruetery, Jack; Pirinenz, Tommi; Trosterud, Trond; Tyers, Francis M.: <a href="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2014/workshops/LREC2014-Workshop-CCURL2014-Proceedings.pdf">Open-Source Infrastructures for Collaborative Work on Under-Resourced Languages.</a> Workshop: Collaboration and Computing for Under-Resourced Languages in the Linked Open Data Era. LREC 2014. p. 71-77</li>
 <li>Moshagen, Sjur N., Tommi A. Pirinen, Trond Trosterud 2013: <a href="http://www.ep.liu.se/ecp_article/index.en.aspx?issue=085;article=031">Building an open-source development infrastructure for language technology projects.</a> Proceedings of the 19th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2013), May 22–24, 2013, Oslo University, Norway. NEALT Proceedings Series 16: 343–352.</li>
		<li>Antonsen, Lene and Trond Trosterud 2011: <a href="http://dspace.utlib.ee/dspace/bitstream/handle/10062/19296/antonsen_trosterud.pdf">Next to nothing – a cheap South Saami disambiguator</a>. NEALT Proceedings Series 2011. Volum 14 [10]. (Cf. also <a href="rigasmapres.pdf">the slides</a> from the presentation held at Workshop in Constraint Grammar Applications, in conjunction with NoDaLiDa 2011, Riga, Latvia, May 11th 2011.)</li>
        <li>Antonsen, L., Wiechetek, L. and T. Trosterud 2010: <a href="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2010/pdf/254_Paper.pdf">Reusing Grammatical Resources for New Languages.</a> In Proceedings of the International conference on Language Resources and Evaluation LREC 2010. p. 2782–2789. ISBN 2-9517408-6-7. Stroudsburg: The Association for Computational Linguistics. (Cf. also <a href="lrec10pres.pdf">the slides</a> from the presentation held at LREC 2010 in Malta May 20th 2010.)</li>
        <li>Antonsen, L., ja T. Trosterud 2010: <a href="http://site.uit.no/aigecala/sda-1-2010-antonsen-ja-trosterud/">Manne dihtor galgá máhttit grammatihka? (Why the computer should know its Sami grammar.)</a> Sámi Dieđalaš Áigečála 2010 (1) s. 3–28. Romsa – Guovdageaidnu.</li>
<li>Trosterud, Trond 2009: <a href="http://dspace.utlib.ee/dspace/bitstream/handle/10062/14289/proceedings.pdf?sequence=1">A constraint grammar for Faroese</a>. NEALT Proceedings Series, Vol 8, pp 1-7. ISSN 1736-6305</li>
		<li>Muhirwe, Jackson and Trond Trosterud 2008: <a href="http://www.aclweb.org/anthology-new/I/I08/I08-3013.pdf">Finite State Solutions For Reduplication In Kinyarwanda Language</a>. Proceedings of the IJCNLP-08 Workshop on NLP for Less Privileged Languages pp. 73-80.</li> 
        <li>Trosterud, T. og L. Wiechetek 2007: <a href="http://www.sgr.fi/sust/sust253/sust253_trosterudjawiechetek.pdf">Disambiguering av homonymi i nord- og lulesamisk.</a> Sámit, sánit, sátnehámit. Riepmočála Pekka Sammallahtii miessemánu 21. beaivve 2007 s. 401–421. Suomalais-Ugrilaisen Seuran Toimituksia 253. Helsinki: Suomalais-Ugrilainen Seura.</li>
<li>Gaup, B., Moshagen, S. N., Omma, T., Palismaa, M., Pieski, T., Trosterud, T. 2006: <a href="http://www.springerlink.com/content/an651qt0g45k55u1/">From Xerox to Aspell: A First Prototype of a North Sámi Speller Based on TWOL Technology.</a> – Anssi Yli-Jyrä – Lauri Karttunen – J. Karhumäki (doaim.), Finite-State Methods and Natural Language Processing. Lecture Notes in Computer Science 4002, s. 306–307. Berlin – Heidelberg: Springer-Verlag.</li>
<li>Trosterud, Trond 2006: <a href="india.pdf">Grammatically based language technology for minority languages</a>. Lesser-Known Languages of South Asia. Status and Policies, Case Studies and Applications of Information Technology. Berlin: Mouton de Gruyter. pp. 293-316.</li>
<li>Trosterud, Trond 2006: <a href="bozen.pdf">Grammar-based Language Technology for the Sámi Languages</a>. Lesser used Languages &amp; Computer Linguistics. Bozen: Europäische Akademie ISBN 88-88906-24-X. s. 133-148</li>
        <li>Trosterud, Trond and Heli Uibo 2005: <a href="trosterud-uibo.pdf">Consonant Gradation in Estonian and Sami: Two-Level Solution.</a> (Eds) Antti Arppe et al. Inquiries into Words, Constraints and Contexts, p. 136–150. CSLI Studies in Computational Linguistics online.</li>
        <li>Moshagen, S., Sammallahti, P., Trosterud, T. 2004: <a href="pst.pdf">Twol at work.</a> Antti Arppe, Lauri Carlson, Krister Lindén, Jussi Piitulainen, Mickael Suominen, Martti Vainio, Hanna Westerlund, Anssi Yli-Jyrä (doaim.), Inquiries into Words, Constraints and Contexts p. 94–105. Stanford, California: CSLI. </li>
        <li>Trosterud, Trond 2004: <a href="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2004/ws/ws2.pdf">Porting morphological analyses and disambiguation to new languages.</a> Julie Carson-Berndsen (ed.) First Steps for Language Documentation of Minority Languages. Computational Linguistic Tools for Morphology, Lexicon and Corpus Compilation. p. 90-92. Paris: European Language Resources Association.</li>
        <li>Trosterud, Trond 2004: Samisk språkteknologi. Henrik Holmboe (red.) Nordisk sprogteknologi. Årbog for Nordisk Sprogteknologisk Forskningsprogram 200-2004. s. 51-58.</li>
        <li>Trosterud, T. 2004: <a href="rvik.pdf">Language technology for endangered languages: Sámi as a case study.</a> (ms.)</li>
        <li>Trosterud, Trond  and Heli Uibo 2005: <a href="http://www.stanford.edu/group/cslipublications/cslipublications/koskenniemi-festschrift/14-trosterud-uibo.pdf">Consonant gradation in Estonian and Sámi: two-level solution</a>. Antti Arppe, Lauri Carlsson, Krister Lindén, Jussi Piitulainen, Mickael Suominen, Martti Vainio, Hanna Westerlund and Anssi Yli-Jyrä (eds.): <a href="http://www.stanford.edu/group/cslipublications/cslipublications/koskenniemi-festschrift/">Inquiries into Words, Constraints and Contexts. Festschrift in the Honour of Kimmo Koskenniemi on his 60th Birthday.</a> pp. 136-150. CSLI Studies in Computational Linguistics ONLINE: CSLI Publications.</li> 
      <li>Trosterud, Trond 2002: Morfologiija rolla sámi giellatenologiijas. Sámi dieđalaš áigečála 1/2002, 90-105</li>
</ul>
     </body>
</document>
