<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
	<header>
		<title>Sami dictionaries for OpenOffice.org 3.x</title>

		<authors>
		<person email="borre.gaup@samediggi.no" name="Børre Gaup" />
		</authors>
	</header>

	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Install dictionaries</title>
			
			<note>
				These installation instructions are for <em>OpenOffice.org 3.x</em>. We have also have <a href="installation_use.html">installation instructions for OpenOffice.org 2.4.x</a>
			</note>
			
			<p>Download <a href="http://divvun.no/static_files/smi.oxt">the dictionaries</a>. This <a href="http://extensions.openoffice.org/">OpenOffice.org extension</a> contains both Northern and Lule Sami dictionaries.</p>
			
			<section>
				<title>Installing an extension for current user</title>
			
				<p>There are several ways to install an extension.</p>
				
				<section>
					<title>Using the Extension Manager dialog.</title>
					
					<p>Open the Extension Manager via Tools-Extension Manager. Click the "Add" button, select the extension in the file chooser dialog and click "OK". You may need to accept a license or agree to replace an existing version of an extension.</p>
				</section>
				
				<section>
					<title>From the download dialog</title>

					<p>When you are about to download an extension the browser or e-mail program may show a dialog where you can choose to open the file with OpenOffice.org or to save it on disk. In the first case, OpenOffice.org will be started and installs the extension. You will be asked if you want to continue installing the extension. Press "OK" to install it.</p>
				</section>
				
				<section>
					<title>By double-clicking</title>

					<p>Double-clicking the extension in a file browser will cause the extension to be installed. The procedure is the same as described before. That is, OpenOffice.org is started, users are asked if they want to continue the installation, and so on.</p>
				</section>

				<section>
					<title>Installing an extension for all users</title>

					<p>To install extensions for all users it is necessary to have write access to the office installation. Open the Extension Manager dialog via Tools-Extension Manager and click the "Add" button. After having selected an extension one will be asked to install it for oneself or all users. Choose "all users".</p>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Using the speller</title>
			<p>To use the speller <a href="install_use.html#Using+the+speller">follow these instructions</a></p>
		</section>
		<p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by
		$Author$</p>
	</body>
</document>