<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>How to use the CG-3 parser vislcg3</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>How to use the vislcg3 parser</title>
      <section>
        <title>Basic usage</title>
	<note>This page is incomplete. Consult the <a href ="http://beta.visl.sdu.dk/cg3/">vislcg3 documentation</a> as well as these notes.</note>
        <p>The command line looks like this (for sme, supposing you stand in the sme directory):</p>
        <source>sme$ cat sometext.txt | preprocess --abbr=bin/abbr.txt | lookup -flags mbTT bin/sme.fst |  ../script/lookup2cg | vislcg3 -g src/sme-dis.rle | less
</source>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Flags and their use</title>
        <p>The vislcg3 program contains a large number of <strong>flags</strong>, or usage options. A list of the flags may be obtained by writing the following command:</p>
        <source>vislcg3 --help</source>
        <p>i.e., by using the flag <em>--help</em>. The most relevant flags for our use are the following:</p>
        <dl>
          <dt>-g src/sme-dis.rle</dt>
          <dd>This flag selects the grammar file</dd>
          <dt>--sections n</dt>
          <dd>This flag sets the number of CONSTRAINT sections that are applied. In this way it is possible to study the effects of one rule set at a time.</dd>
          <dt>--trace</dt>
          <dd>This flag tells the parser to include information of what constraint rules are invoked in each concrete case. The flag is crucial for studying the effects of the different rules.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>References</title>
	<p>Didriksen, Tino 2007: Constraint Grammar Manual. 3rd version of the CG formalism variant. http://beta.visl.sdu.dk/cg3/</p>
        <p>Karlsson, Fred; Atro Voutilainen, Juha Heikkilä and Arto Anttila 1995: Constraint Grammar. A Language-Independent System for Parsing Unrestricted Text. Mouton the Gruyter.</p>
        <p>Tapanainen, Pasi 1996: The Constraint Grammar Parser CG-2. University of Helsinki Publications No. 27.</p>

      </section>
      
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
