<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>How to use the CG-2 parser vislcg</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>How to use the vislcg parser</title>
      <section>
        <title>Basic usage</title>
        <p>The command line looks like this (for sme, supposing you stand in the sme directory):</p>
        <source>sme$ cat sometext.txt | preprocess --abbr=bin/abbr.txt | lookup -flags mbTT bin/sme.fst |  ../script/lookup2cg | vislcg --grammar=src/sme-dis.rle | less
</source>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Flags and their use</title>
        <p>The vislcg program contains 18 <strong>flags</strong>, or usage options. A list of the flags may be obtained by writing the following command:</p>
        <source>vislcg --help</source>
        <p>i.e., by using the flag <em>--help</em>. The most relevant flags for our use are the following:</p>
        <dl>
          <dt>--grammar=src/sme-dis.rle</dt>
          <dd>This flag selects the grammar file. The &quot;=&quot; symbol is optional.</dd>
          <dt>--sections=n</dt>
          <dd>This flag sets the number of CONSTRAINT sections that are applied. In this way it is possible to study the effects of one rule set at a time.</dd>
          <dt>--trace</dt>
          <dd>This flag tells the parser to include information of what constraint rules are invoked in each concrete case. The flag is crucial for studying the effects of the different rules.</dd>
          <dt>--minimal</dt>
          <dd>The flag --minimal is used together with the flag --trace. With this flag only the line number of the rule is given. Without the --minimal flag, the parser also lists the rule in question.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>For reference: Tapanainen's original CG-2 parser</title>
      <p>Tapanainen's original CG-2 parser <em>mdis</em> is available from <a href="http://www.connexor.com" >Connexor</a>. A copy of the parser is available for staff and students on the computer of the ling.dept at the U of Helsinki, at ~tapanain/conexor/mdis/bin/. The parser cannot be used outside this computer.</p>
      <p>The CG-2 parser is actually two different CG-2 parsers (Tap96 mentions 4 more parsers, this information is obsolete):</p>
      <dl>
        <dt>mdis</dt>
        <dd>mapping and disambiguation</dd>
        <dt>mdis.trace</dt>
        <dd>mapping and disambiguation, but with id numbers of the rules.</dd>
      </dl>
      <section>
        <title>The flags</title>
        <p>This list given here is not complete, but includes only relevant flags. For a full list, see Tap96.</p>
        <dl>
          <dt>--grammar=grammarfile.rle</dt>
          <dd>obligatorily for parsing (note the symbol &quot;=*, in Tap96 this is still not included)</dd>
          <dt>--sections=n</dt>
          <dd>sets the number (n) of CONSTRAINT sections. By default, all sections are applied.</dd>
          <dt>--check-only</dt>
          <dd>the parser does not apply rules</dd>
        </dl>
        <p>Thus, CG-2 differs from vislcg, that consists of only one parser (<em>vislcg</em>), but has more flags (also more flags than CG-2).</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <p>Tapanainen, Pasi 1996: The Constraint Grammar Parser CG-2. University of Helsinki Publications No. 27.</p>

      </section>
      
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
