<html xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en">
   <head>
      <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8">
      <title>How to use PuTTY.exe</title>
      <authors>
         <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud"></person>
      </authors>
   </head>
   <body>
      <p>PuTTY is a program that makes it possible to work on a remote Linux
         machine from a Windows PC computer.
      </p>
      <h1>How to use PuTTY.exe</h1>
      <p>You need two files, PuTTY.exe and psftp.exe. They can both be found
         and downloaded from the same site.
      </p>
      <h2>What is PuTTY.exe and psftp.exe?</h2>
      <p>Use the terminal: <strong>PuTTY.exe</strong> is a program that makes Windows users
         establish a secure connection to Unix (and Linux) terminals, among
         other things.
      </p>
      <p>Copy files to and from the terminal: <strong>psftp.exe</strong> is a program that makes it
         possible to copy files from victorio to your local machine and vice
         versa.
      </p>
      <h2>How to get the programs</h2>
      <p>Go to the <a href="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/download.html">PuTTY Download Page</a>. 
         Download both <strong>PuTTY.exe</strong> and <strong>psftp.exe</strong>.
      </p>
      <h2>How to set up PuTTY and connect to the terminal</h2>
      <p>Doubleclick on the PuTTY.exe icon, and get a small box in
         return.  The <strong>first</strong> time you use putty with a new
         terminal, the following, in this order:
      </p>
      <ol>
         <li>Click on <code>Translation</code> in the category Window in the leftmost box.
         </li>
         <li>The
            default translation is <code>ISO-8859-1</code>, you should
            open the list and choose <code>UTF-8</code></li>
         <li>Thereafter, click <code>Session</code> (the topmost node)
         </li>
         <li>To the right, under  "Host
            Name", write <em>gtlab.uit.no</em>(or whatever terminal you log on to).
         </li>
         <li>Make sure Connection type is <code>SSH</code></li>
         <li>Give the connection a
            name, e.g. "victorio" (in the space one field down).
         </li>
         <li>Click the <code>Save</code> button
         </li>
         <li>Now, the name ("victorio") appears on the list of predefined
            servers. To log in, double click on it (or select and click 
            <code>Open</code>.
         </li>
      </ol>
      <p><strong>NOTE!</strong> There is a bug in the present PuTTY
         version: The Sami keyboard is able to write all characters, except 
         č,  ŋ and ŧ.
         All characters are displayed on the screen, though, and you can copy
         in the problematic čŋŧ.
      </p>
      <h2>How to copy files between the terminal and your own machine</h2>
      <p>On <a href="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/download.html">the PuTTY download page</a>, doubleclick
         on the psftp.exe icon. Write "open gtlab.uit.no" (or your server name) at the
         prompt. Give your user name and password. To get the file file1.txt from
         the remote machine to your own machine, you write
      </p>
      <p>get file1.txt file2.txt</p>
      <p>(advice: Use a different filename for the file, so that you do not need to risk deleting
         your work if you use get instead of put etc.). To copy a file file3.txt which is on
         <em>C:\Users\MyName</em> from your PC to the remote machine , you write
      </p>
      <p>put C:\Users\MyName\file3.txt file4.txt The command is <code>get sourcefile resultfile</code> (and
         the same for put). In order to copy e.g. the file
         main/gt/sme/src/noun-sme-lex.txt to your own machine, write this command:
      </p>
      <p>get gt/sme/src/noun-sme-lex.txt noun.txt</p>
      <p>Note that psftp.exe makes it possible to use standard unix
         commands. Cf. <a href="http://the.earth.li/~sgtatham/putty/0.52/htmldoc/Chapter6.html">the psftp.exe
            help file</a> for a list of commands.
      </p>
      <p>Remember: <em>putty</em> is a program for working on the remote computer, 
         <em>psftp</em> is there for copying files to and fro.
      </p>
      <h2>Copy many files at the same time from the terminal to your machine with psftp.exe</h2>
      <p>The psftp.exe program cannot use the * notation when copying files,
         one must write the name of each file separately. The way of copying
         many files in one operation is to use putty.exe to lump them together
         in one archive file, and then use psftp.exe to move that file to your
         local machine, and unpack it there. The following command makes an archive
         files.zip of all files ending in .txt in the terminal:
      </p>
      <p>zip files.zip *.txt</p>
      <p>Then you must copy the files to your local machine. In order to do
         that, open a window in psftp.exe, and give the following command, just
         as described before (note that s.tar is so big that it might take some
         time to download it.):
      </p>
      <p>get files.zip f.zip</p>
      <p>The file files.zip may then be opened on your local
         Windows machine with the winzip program (or similarily).
      </p>
      <h2>Copy many files at the same time from your machine to the terminal with psftp.exe</h2>
      <p>Put all the files you want to use in a folder, say its name is filmappe. Right-click
         and choose
      </p>
      <p>move to &gt; a zipped archive</p>
      <p> (Norwegian: Send til &gt; Komprimert (zippet) mappe)</p>
      <p>The resulting file is named filmappe.zip (even though the .zip is not displayed).
         Copy the file as before, in psftp.exe:
      </p>
      <p><code>put filmappe.zip f.zip</code></p>
      <p>In the terminal (in putty) you then open it by writing</p>
      <p><code>unzip f.zip</code></p>
   </body>
</html>