<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>How to use SVN</title>
  </header>

  <body>
    <p>SVN is a program which keeps track of all the different versions of our
    source files. People familiar with its predecessor, <em>cvs</em> should read
    on. If you have not heard of cvs, then read <a
    href="docu-cvs-user.html">this document</a> (concentrate on the big picture,
    and ignore the details). This documentation is written because of our
    transition to SVN. When the transition period is over, we will rewrite these
    pages. While waiting, this page will contain information useful for our
    present cvs users.</p>

    <p>Our main subversion repository is at the address <a
    href="https://victorio.uit.no/langtech/">http://victorio.uit.no/langtech/</a>.
    Subversion documentation is available as a <a
    href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.4/index.html">browsable book</a>.</p>

    <section>
      <title>Graphical Subversion clients</title>

      <p>If you want to use a graphical Subversion client, please see the
      following pages for descriptions of some alternatives, and their setup for
      our repositories:</p>

      <ul>
        <li><a href="docu-svn-user-rapidsvn.html">RapidSVN</a> - a
        multi-platform, open-source GUI front-end (<a
        href="http://rapidsvn.tigris.org/">home page</a>)</li>

        <li><a href="docu-svn-user-versionsapp.html">Versions.app</a> - a Mac
        only, commercial client (<a href="http://www.versionsapp.com/">home
        page</a>)</li>

        <li><a href="docu-svn-user-svnx.html">SvnX</a> - a Mac only, open-source
        client (home page <a href="http://code.google.com/p/svnx/">here</a> and
        <a
        href="http://www.lachoseinteractive.net/en/community/subversion/svnx/features/">here</a>)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Please follow the recommendations for daily routines at the end of this
      document!</p>

      <p>The major benefit of graphical clients is that they make some
      operations that much easier and faster. YMMV, and you have to try to find
      what suits your working habits best yourself. In the end, a combination of
      graphical and command-line tools could be the best approach.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Use svn on the command line</title>

      <note>This document describes how to check out and work with svn. For
      issues related to the conversion from cvs to svn, read <a
      href="svnconv_remember.html">this document</a>.</note>

      <p>To <em>check out</em> means that you copy all the documents that our
      projects are working on to your computer.</p>

      <section>
        <title>The first commands</title>

        <p>Go to your home directory (write <code>cd</code>), and give the
        following command:</p>

        <source>
svn co https://victorio.uit.no/langtech/trunk main --username &lt;your_username&gt;
</source>

        <p>... where you have replaced &lt;your_username&gt; with the username
        you have aquired from the admin. This will enable you to check in your
        work. If you don't have a user name or just want to browse our code,
        just skip the username.</p>

        <p>After you have checked out, please run the following script, and
        follow the on-screen instructions:</p>

        <source>
main/gt/script/gtsetup.sh
</source>

        <p>With the above commands, you have now on your local computer a copy
        of the source code and the environment is set up properly.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Frequently used commands</title>

        <p>Now that you have checked out your repository, you can use a set of
        commands to manipulate your copy of the source code. We recommend to
        always <em>update</em> the repository before you begin to edit files
        inside it. After having edited some files you usually want to have an
        overview of which files have been <em>modified</em>. To share our work
        with the others we <em>check in</em> our work. We can also <em>add</em>,
        <em>delete</em>, <em>move</em> and <em>copy</em> files inside the
        repository. A brief overview of the commands needed for these actions is
        given below, for further details see the references at the end of this
        document.</p>

        <dl>
          <dt>Update your working copy</dt>

          <dd>svn up</dd>

          <dt>Scedule a file for addition</dt>

          <dd>svn add filename</dd>

          <dt>Scedule a file for deletion</dt>

          <dd>svn delete filename</dd>

          <dt>You may also copy and move files and directories with these two
          commands, but read about them in the svn book first:</dt>

          <dd>svn copy filename<br /> svn move filename</dd>

          <dt>Examine your changes</dt>

          <dd>svn status</dd>

          <dt>Examine the file history</dt>

          <dd>svn log filename</dd>

          <dt>Compare your modified file to the version in the repository</dt>

          <dd>svn diff filename</dd>

          <dt>Compare some earlier versions, say here versions 123 and 120</dt>

          <dd>svn diff -r 123:120 filename</dd>

          <dt>Possibly undo the changes you just checked in</dt>

          <dd>svn revert filename</dd>

          <dt>Resolve Conflicts (Merge Others' Changes)</dt>

          <dd>svn update<br /> svn resolved</dd>

          <dt>Commit your changes</dt>

          <dd>svn ci -m "Your short message here" filename<br /> (Note that the
          above changes, add, delete, copy, move, must all be committed by ci in
          order to take effect)</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Ignoring items</title>

        <p>The Subversion <code>svn:ignore</code> property is very similar in
        syntax and function to the CVS <code>.cvsignore</code> file. In fact, if
        you are migrating a CVS working copy to Subversion, you can directly
        migrate the ignore patterns by using the <code>.cvsignore</code> file as
        input file to the <code>svn propset</code> command:</p>

        <source>$ svn propset svn:ignore -F .cvsignore . 
property 'svn:ignore' set on '.' 
$</source>

        <p>More details about ignoring files can be found in <em>Chapter 3:
        Advanced Topics</em>, in the section <em>Ignoring Unversioned
        Items</em>, in the <a href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">SVN
        book</a>.</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>How often do I check in?</title>

      <p>Always check in the files at the end of the day. If you know that other
      people are working on the same file, you should check in more often than
      that. You should also check in after you have done major revisions.
      Remember to compile the program before you check in, so that you know you
      do not check in a defect file.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>What do I write in the log message</title>

      <p>The best way to learn to write good log messages is to read other log
      messages. Pick a file (e.g. twol-sme.txt, sme-lex.fst), and read the log
      (the command is <strong>svn log filename | less</strong>). If the log
      message tells you what you want to know, then it is a good log
      message.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Further reading</title>

      <p>The <a
      href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.4/svn.tour.cycle.html">Basic work
      cycle</a> in the <a href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com">SVN book</a> covers
      daily usage in great detail. <a
      href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.4/svn.forcvs.html">Appendix B</a>
      covers some details for users accustomed to CVS.</p>

      <p>The <a href="http://www.rapidsvn.org/index.php/Main_Page">RapidSVN
      wiki</a> has a <a
      href="http://www.rapidsvn.org/index.php/Documentation#Tutorial.2C_Part_1">tutorial</a>
      that covers our daily usage pattern.</p>
    </section>

    <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date: 2008-11-05 19:52:54 +0200
    (ons, 05 nov 2008) $, by $Author$</p>
  </body>
</document>
