<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>Conversion scripts</title>
    <authors>
      <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
      <person email="borre.gaup@samediggi.no" name="Børre Gaup" />
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Conversion scripts</title>

      <p>The conversion scripts are located in
      <code>gt/script</code>. They are of two different types:
      perl scripts (*.pl) and xfst scripts. The xfst scripts are compiled,
      they have filename.regex as source file names and filename.fst as
      binary file names.</p>

      <p>The scripts have different functions. Some scripts convert input text
      to the internal format used by the program, whereas other scripts convert
      the output of the program into a format suitable for output.</p>

      <p>Note that the unix utility <strong>iconv</strong> contains ready-made
      conversion routines for many code tables. The syntax is as follows:</p>

      <p>
    <code>$ iconv --from-code=ISO-8859-1 --to-code=UTF-8 &lt; old_file
    > new_file</code>
      </p>

      <p>A list of code tables is listed with <strong>iconv --list</strong>.
      This of course does not help in converting text to our internal format,
      but in the future it may be used for conversion to utf-8.</p>

      <section>
         <title>Naming the scripts</title>
     <p>The scripts are named &quot;sourceform-targetform.scripttype&quot;.
     The perl script converting Latin 6 input to the internal 7-bit digraph
     system <em>á, c1, d1, n1, s1, t1, z1</em>, is called
     <strong>latin6-7bit.pl</strong>.</p>

     <p>There are at the moment script for converting from ws2, Latin6 and
     mac (here called &quot;linmac&quot;, since mac files are translated
     to something else when the files are moved to Linux. &quot;Something
     else&quot; is here called &quot;linmac&quot; (mac as observed on
     Linux), and taken as a starting point for the conversion script.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
    <title>Scripts converting input text to and from internal digraphs (&quot;7bit&quot;)</title>
    <section>
      <title>Perl scripts</title>

      <p>The perl scripts contain conversion lines of the format
      <strong>s/\273/t1/g</strong>. This line converts a t-stroke to t1.
      The code position (in the code table Latin 6, used a.o. by Statens
      Kartverk) is hexadecimal BB. Perl uses octal notation, and the octal
      value of BB is 273.</p>

          <p>Note that there are two different scripts, utf8-7bit.pl and
      utf8.pl. The former converts from utf8 to 7bit, the other one is
      some sort of all-in-one-script that converts from different formats
      (mac saved as utf8, text written on Win9x saved as utf8, etc. to
      7-bit. Testing is needed to see whether this is a relevant
      partition, in any case, the utf8-7bit.pl works in cases where the
      input signal has <strong>not</strong> been corrupted, i.e. it takes
      real utf8 as input.</p>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>xfst scripts</title>

      <p>The &lt;encoding>-7bit.regex files are files that convert from
      the given encoding to the internal format.</p>

      <p>The 7bit-&lt;encoding>.regex files are files that convert to the
      given encoding from the internal format.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Compiling .regex files</title>

        <p>To make use of the .regex files you may have to compile them to
        .fst files. Go to the <em>script</em> directory and have a look at
        the .regex and .fst files. If the .regex file is older than the
        .fst file with the same name, you may use the .fst file right on,
        and you do not need to compile. If the .fst file is older or do
        not exist, you must compile it. Do that by <strong>while in the
        script directory</strong> type the command:</p>

            <source>make all
</source>
          </section>

      <section>
        <title>Using the resulting .fst files for North Sámi</title>

        <p>In order to convert from encoding X to internal format, be in
        the script directory, and type the following command:</p>

            <source>cat &lt;&amp;lt;encoding>-filename> | lookup -flags mbTT -f &lt;encoding>-7bit.fst
        </source>

        <p>It will will convert a file from a given encoding to the
        internal format.</p>

            <p>In order to analyse a file in a given encoding, go to the
        gt/sme directory. To analyze a file in the ws2 (aka. levi, WinSam2)
        encoding type the command</p>

        <source>cat  | preprocess --abbr=bin/abbr.txt | lookup -flags mbTT -f ws2-sme | less
        </source>

            <p>Upon executing this command the input file will first be
        tokenized, then converted to the internal format, analyzed and the
        output will be in the same encoding as the input file.</p>

            <note>XXX But is this a good idea? we must evaluate this. It is
        hard to see how anyone would like his input back to ws2 on a Linux
        terminal. Tests on input is needed here.TT</note>

            <p>The lookup file ws2-file has this content (The file format is
        documented in Beesley/Karttunen, p. 442):</p>

        <source>sme sme.fst
fws2    ../script/ws2-7bit.fst
tws2    ../script/7bit-ws2.fst

fws2 sme tws2
        </source>
            <p>This file converts the input from the ws2 encoding to the
        internal format. The input will then be analyzed with the sme.fst
        file and the result is converted back to the ws2 format.</p>

        <p>The other &lt;encoding>-sme files follow the same pattern.</p>

      </section>
    </section>
      </section>

      <section>
    <title>The case conversion scripts</title>

    <section>
      <title>Initial capital letter</title>

      <p>The most improtant caseconvertion scripts are case.regex
      (caseconv.fst). They are different form language to language, and
      located in the language-specific directories. They form an integrated
      part of the Makefiles, and the resulting parsers contain the ability
      of recognising initial capital letters.</p>

    </section>

    <section>

      <title>Letters in all caps</title>

      <p>There are also scripts to allow for words written in all caps,
      called allcaps.regex. By the help of such scripts,
      (&quot;Duodji&quot; is accepted, as is &quot;DUODJI&quot;,
      but &quot;DuoDji&quot; is not. These are also located in the src
      directories (so far only for sme), and are integrated in the
      Makefile. But the resulting allcaps.fst is not compiled together
      with sme.fst into a single transducer, as this would have resulted
      in a too large network. Instead, it is kept separate in the sme/bin
      directory, and when needed, it may be invoked by the following
      command (assuming you stand in gt/sme):</p>

          <p>... | lookup -flags mbTT -f src/cap-sme | ...</p>

      <p>Note that the lookup script file is located in sme/src, but the
      binary allcaps.fst that the cap-sme file refers to, is located in
      sme/bin.</p>

    </section>
      </section>

      <section>
    <title>The spellrelax scripts</title>

    <p>South and Lule Saami have scripts to allow for different
    practices for writing <em>ï¿½</em> (as ï¿½or i) and for the
    Norwegian/Swedish ï¿½ï¿½and ï¿½ mix. These are xfst scripts,
    integrated in the makefiles of sma and smj.</p>

      </section>

      <section>

        <title>The scripts converting 7bit to html</title>

        <p>Børre?</p>
        <p>or should this be documented on the webinterace page?</p>

      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Scripts converting from &quot;alien&quot; fileformats to 7bit</title>
        <section>

          <title>pdf to 7bit converters</title>

          <p>The script pdfto7bit.pl is a script that converts pdf files to
      7bit. It is used like this:</p>

      <source>pdfto7bit.pl [option] &lt;filename></source>

      <p>The options allowed are:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>-e: output the even pages</li>
        <li>-o: output the odd pages</li>
      </ul>

      <p>To use it you will have to have the <em>gt/script</em> catalog in
      your path. Type this at the command prompt.</p>

      <source>PATH=&quot;~/[path to the gt directory]/gt/script:$PATH&quot;
      </source>
      <p>After this you can type &quot;pdfto7bit.pl&quot; at the command
      prompt to use it. Typical uses are shown below</p>

      <ul>
        <li>To analyze a pdf file, go to the <em>gt/sme</em> directory,
        and type: <code>pdfto7bit.pl &lt;filename.pdf> | preprocess
        --abbr=bin/abbr.txt |lookup -flags mbTT sme.fst | less.</code>
        The more advanced uses, documented in the
        <a href="docu-sme-manual.html" >sme-manual</a>
        can also be used.</li>
        <li>
          <code>for pdffile in [directory of pdf files]/*.pdf
          do
          pdfto7bit.pl $pdffile > [directory of text files]/`basename $pdffile .pdf`.txt
          done
        </code>. This command takes a batch of pdf files, converts them to text files and saves them in a given directory. The command <em>`basename $pdffile .pdf`.txt</em> assures that a pdf file named: foo.pdf is saved as foo.txt.</li>
        <li>Some pdf documents have sámi and norwegian text on every other page. The options <em>-e</em> and <em>-o</em> is to overcome this problem. If the sámi text is on the even pages of the offending document type the following at the command prompt: <source>pdfto7bit.pl -e &lt;name of offending file></source>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
      </section>
      
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
