<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>How to use PuTTY.exe</title>
    <authors>
      <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <p>PuTTY is a program that makes it possible to work on a remote Linux
    machine from a Windows PC computer.</p>

    <section>
      <title>How to use PuTTY.exe</title>

      <p>You need two files, PuTTY.exe and psftp.exe. They can both be found
      and downloaded from the same site.</p>

      <section>
        <title>What is PuTTY.exe and psftp.exe?</title>

        <p><strong>PuTTY.exe</strong> is a program that makes Windows users
        establish a secure connection to Unix (and Linux) terminals, among
        other things. <strong>psftp.exe</strong> is a program that makes it
        possible to copy files from victorio to your local machine and vice
        versa.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>How to get the programs</title>

        <p>They are found may places, a.o. at <a
        href="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/download.html">here</a>,
        earlier also <a
        href="http://putty.gyron.net/">here</a>. Search for "putty
        download" if the links are broken. Go to the Download page,
        download both PuTTY.exe and psftp.exe, and put them in a
        folder where you store your programs. Make an alias somewhere
        (e.g. on the desktop, or drag them to the taskbar on the
        bottom of your screen) so that you can find it later.</p>

        <section>
          <title>How to set up PuTTY and connect to victorio</title>

          <p>Doubleclick on the PuTTY.exe icon, and get a small box in
          return.  To the right, you are prompted for "Host
          Name". Write <em>user@victorio.uit.no </em>(where
          <em>user</em> is your username).  Give the connection a
          name, e.g. "victorio" (in the space one field down). Then,
          click <code>Terminal</code> to the left, and choose UTF-8
          (or, in recent versions: In the leftmost box
          (<code>Category</code>) of the Putty settings box, under
          <code>Window</code> choose <code>Translation</code>. The
          default translation is <code>ISO-8859-1</code>, you should
          open the list and choose <code>UTF-8</code>. Font size 8
          gives you a normal amount on text, and most monitors give
          you 50 lines of text. After having made these choices, go
          back to the first (or rightmost) menu, and click on
          <em>save</em> in the menu to the rignt. Make sure
          <strong>SSH</strong> is chosen under "Protocol", and click
          on "Open" at the bottom of the window.</p>

          <p>If everything is ok, you will find a new window in front of you,
          prompting for your user name. Write it, and then press the ENTER
          key, and write your password, followed by ENTER. Then you are logged
          in.</p>

          <p>This presupposes that you have a Saami keyboard on your PC. From
          2004 onwards all new Windows XP systems have Saami keyboards
          installed, you may find it by right-clicking the keyboard symbol, or
          via the Control Panel.</p>

          <p><strong>NOTE!</strong> There is a bug in the present PuTTY
          version: All Saami characters work perfectly, except the č character
          (c-caron), for some strange reason (what you get is plain c), even
          though č works in other programs. TODO: Report and fix. </p>

          <p>After the session, remember logging out by writing
          <strong>logout</strong>. Also, remember that you may have several
          windows open at the same time (just open the second, third etc. in the same way as the first).</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>How to copy files between victorio and your own machine</title>

        <p>On the gyron download page referred to above, doubleclick
        on the psftp.exe icon. Write "open victorio.uit.no" at the
        prompt. Give your user name and password. To get files from
        victorio, you write "get", and to copy files to victorio, you
        write "put". The syntax is "get sourcefile resultfile" (and
        the same for put). In order to copy e.g. the file
        gt/sme/src/noun-sme-lex.txt, write this command:</p>

        <p>get gt/sme/src/noun-sme-lex.txt noun.txt</p>

        <p>Since it easy to get confused with the get and put commands, I
        always use another filename for the file I copy to. If you use the
        same name twice, and copy the wrong direction, then the old file will
        replace the new one, and your work will be lost.</p>

        <p>Note that psftp.exe makes it possible to use standard unix
        commands. Cf. <a href="http://putty.gyron.net/...">the psftp.exe
        help file</a> for a list of commands.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Copy many files at the same time with psftp.exe</title>

        <p>The psftp.exe program cannot use the * notation when copying files,
        one must write the name of each file separately. The way of copying
        many files in one operation is to use putty.exe to lump them together
        in one archive file, and then use psftp.exe to move that file to your
        local machine, and unpack it there. We give two actual examples. The
        first copies all the html files from the doc catalog, and the other
        one copies all the txt file from the sme/src catalog. The first step
        is to open a window with putty.exe, and make two archive files. We
        assume that you stand in your home directory, and write the following
        commands, the first to copy the html files, the second to copy the
        program's source files.</p>

        <p>tar cf - gt/doc/*html | gzip &gt; d.tar.gz<br />tar cf -
        gt/sme/src/*txt | gzip &gt; s.tar.gz</p>

        <p>The file names d and s are chosen arbitrarily in order to avoid
        writing long names, the suffixes .tar and .gz indicates the file type
        (the files are compressed twice, first by tar and then by gzip). If
        you want to actually see what files you copy, you may write
        <strong>cvf</strong> instead of <strong>cf</strong> after
        <strong>tar</strong>, the v instructs the tar command to tell what it
        does. If you only copy small files, or have a very fast computer, the
        gzip part is not necessary, then a simpler "tar cf d.tar gt/doc/*html"
        will do, the gzip part of the command just makes download time 1/3
        shorter than tar only).</p>

        <p>Then you must copy the files to your local machine. In order to do
        that, open a window in psftp.exe, and give the following command, just
        as described before (note that s.tar is so big that it might take some
        time to download it.):</p>

        <p>get d.tar.gz d2.tar.gz<br />get s.tar.gz s2.tar.gz</p>

        <p>The files d2.tar and s2.tar may then be opened on your local
        Windows machine with the winzip program (doubleclick on the d2.tar and
        s2.tar files, and Winzip will open. Answer <strong>yes</strong> to
        open the .gz file, then select all the files that will appear as a
        list (ctrl-A) and click on "Extract"), and as a result you have all
        the documentation files, and all the source text files, on your local
        Windows PC.</p>

      </section>
      <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by $Author$</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>