<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
    <header>
        <title>How to use the morphological parsers</title>
        <authors>
            <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud"/>
        </authors>
    </header>
   <body>
        <section>
            <title>Preamble</title>
            <p>Setting up the environment (You probably did this already):</p>
            <ol>
                <li><a href="../infra/GettingStarted.html">Set up the computer</a> and <a href="docu-svn-user.html">download the source files</a></li>
                <li><a href="../infra/infraremake/GettingStartedWithTheNewInfra.html">Build the programs for analysis (= compile the transducers)</a>.</li>
            </ol>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Analysing and generating words</title>
            <ol>
                <li>Analysis, write <code>u</code> and the 3-letter language code using the (basic) xfst program, e.g. for North Saami,
                write <code>usme</code>, and &lt;ENTER&gt;. Then write the words that shall be analysed, one word at a time, followed by &lt;ENTER&gt;.
                To leave analysis mode, press <code>ctrl C</code>.</li>
                <li>For generation, use <code>d</code> instead of u, e.g. <code>dsme</code>.
                Then write lemma and grammatical tags (in the same form as was given as output, followed by &lt;ENTER&gt;.</li>
                <li>For testing, you may also write a file with one wordform on each line, and then feed that to
                the analyser (example here is for Inari Saami, with a file <em>testfile.txt</em>):</li>
            </ol>
            <p><code>cat testfile.txt | usmn | less</code></p>
            <p>If you want to use <em>hfst</em> instead of xfst, write <code>husme</code> and <code>hdsme</code>. The actual command behind these aliases are revealed by writing <code>alias usme</code> etc. If this commands gives no answer, you should run command <code>sh gtsetup.sh</code>. See the documentation in the preamble.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Text analysis (xfst)</title>

            <p>We have set up aliases for text analysis (xfst only), the
            aliases contain a pipeline combining perl pre- and
            postprocessing with xfst transducers and constraint
            grammar. These aliases may be written anywhere (replace "sme"
            with your own language code).</p>

            <dl>
                <dt>smedis</dt>
                <dd>Gives a sentence analysis of North Saami</dd>
                <dt>smedep</dt>
                <dd>Gives a dependency analysis of North Saami</dd>
                <dt>smedist</dt>
                <dd>Gives a sentence analysis of North Saami, in trace mode (showing which dis rules work)</dd>
                <dt>smedept</dt>
                <dd>Gives a dependency analysis of North Saami, in trace mode (showing which dep rules work)</dd>
            </dl>

            <p>These aliases may be used in two ways: either write the alias followed by a sentence in quotes</p>
            <source>smedis "Mun lean boahtán."</source>

            <p>Or, alternatively, pipe a file through it:</p>
            <source>cat testfile.txt | smedis</source>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Text analysis (hfst)</title>

            <p>For hfst, we have an alternative procedure for
            preprocessing text, using transducers instead of perl. The
            command to tokenise, analyse and print the output in a CG
            compatible format is:</p>

            <source>cat testfile.txt | hfst-tokenise --giella-cg tools/tokenisers/tokeniser-disamb-gt-desc.pmhfst</source>

            <p>In case the transducer contains weights, the constraint grammar may make use of them, as follows</p>

            <source>cat text | hfst-tokenise --giella-cg tools/tokenisers/tokeniser-disamb-gt-desc.pmhfst | ...</source>

            <p>Please note that the file
                <code>tools/tokenisers/tokeniser-disamb-gt-desc.pmhfst</code> is
                not built by default. To enable building it, configure as
                follows:</p>
            <source>./configure --with-hfst --enable-tokenisers</source>

            <p>This setup is experimental, so there are no aliases yet</p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Output manipulation</title>

            <p>(Warning: this part contains basic unix commands only.)</p>
            <p>Instead of just showing the result on the screen as running text (as above), much can be done to manipulate
            it. Here are some examples, all the textstrings should be added after the <em>smedis</em> etc. above.</p>

            <p><code>| grep '+N+Pl' &gt; plnouns</code><br/> (to get all plural nouns and save them to the file
            <em>plnouns</em>)</p>
            <p><code>| grep -v '\?' | cut -f2 | sort | uniq -c | sort -nr | less </code><br/> (to get a frequency
            list of the lexemes that the parser recognizes.</p>
            <p><code>| grep '\?' | sort | uniq -c | sort -nr | less </code> <br/> (to get a frequency list of the
            <strong>words</strong> that the parser does not recognize)</p>
            <p><code>| grep '\+\?' | sort | uniq -c | sort -nr | less </code> <br/> (to get a frequency list of the
            <strong>word forms</strong> that the parser does not recognize)</p>
        </section>

        
    </body>
</document>
