<html xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en">
   <head>
      <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8">
      <title>A crash course in lynx</title>
      <authors>
         <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud"></person>
      </authors>
   </head>
   <body>
      <h1>What is lynx?</h1>
      <p>Lynx is a text-based browser, offering "internet with no pictures".
         It can be used to read the documentation if you work on gtlab rather
         than on your local machine. After we ported our documentation to xml and
         forrest, it is not required in the same way as before (you may use your
         favourite browser on the files on your local Mac), but it still has its
         friends and admirers.
      </p>
      <h1>A crash course in lynx</h1>
      <h2>Basic commands</h2>
      <ul>
         <li><strong>Start lynx::
               </strong><br>Write <em>lynx filename</em></li>
         <li><strong>Quit lynx::
               </strong><br>Type q
         </li>
         <li><strong>Follow link::
               </strong><br>Right arrow (or: Enter)
         </li>
         <li><strong>Go back::
               </strong><br>Left arrow
         </li>
         <li><strong>Move to next and previous links in the document::
               </strong><br>Down arrow, up arrow
         </li>
         <li><strong>See the link history:
               </strong><br>Press the Bcksp (Left Delete) key
         </li>
      </ul>
      <h2>How to get more help</h2>
      <p>Lynx is the text-based web browser. It works just like Netscape and
         other browsers, except that it has no pictures, only text. The reason
         why we use it in this project is that it is convenient to use on
         remote machines in cases when a graphical interface cannot be
         established (which is the case for our project). Many users prefer
         lynx to graphical browsers in any case.
      </p>
      <p>Lynx is started by writing <em>lynx filename.html</em> at the
         prompt. Lynx also read plain textfiles, but it is made to handle html
         documents.
      </p>
      <p>The basic help is displayed at the bottom of each lynx page. Read
         it, and try out the different options. Here they are:
      </p>
      <pre xml:space="preserve">----------------------------------------------------------------
Arrow keys: Up and Down to move.  Right to follow a link;
Left to go back. H)elp O)ptions P)rint G)o M)ain screen
Q)uit /=search [delete]=history list
----------------------------------------------------------------
</pre>
      <p>The best way of getting to know lynx is thus to press the h key, so
         this page will be kept short. Just some advices to get you
         started:
      </p>
      <p>In order to be easy to use, lynx should show links as numbers. If
         the links you see are not numbered (like this: [4]), you should change
         the lynx settings. Do this:
      </p>
      <p>Press the key <em>o</em> (for "option"), go down to "keypad mode"
         under "Keyboard input". Press enter, and chose "Links are numbered".
         Use the arrow keys and go back up to the top of the document, tick the
         option "Save options to disk", and go then to "Accept changes" and
         press enter. Now, the links should be numbered, and they can be
         accessed by printing the appropriate number and pressing enter.
      </p>
      <p>As the basic help says, the arrow keys are the most important ones.
         On some terminal connections, it may be tricky to get the arrow keys
         working as they should. If you are in such a position (arrows do not
         work), there are workarounds (TAB to move, enter to follow link, and
         Backspace to get a list of previously visited sites). This is
         cumbersome, but not impossible, I lived with my Lynx like that because
         I couldn't find a guru to help me with the keyboard settings. Don't
         give up like I did, try to find someone to fix the keyboard settings
         for you so that the arrow keys will work. For scrolling down, press
         space or PgDn, for scrolling up, press - (dash, to the right of . on
         Nordic keyboards) or PgUp.
      </p>
      <p>Lynx is an excellent browser, but it has one weakness: It cannot
         read tables. If you need to read tables (e.g. for the documentation on
         the testing interface, or on South Sami, you need <a href="docu-links.html">links</a>, a browser that is very much like
         lynx.
      </p>
   </body>
</html>