<html xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en">
   <head>
      <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8">
      <title>How to use TortoiseSVN</title>
   </head>
   <body>
      <h1>Using SVN on a Windows machine: TortoiseSVN</h1>
      <h2>The program</h2>
      <p>TortoiseSVN is a graphical program for using SVN. It can be downloaded from <a href="http://tortoisesvn.net/">tortoisesvn.net</a>. Just download the program and install it as any other Windows program. This is the
         program we recommend for using SVN on Windows.
      </p>
      <p></p>
      <h2>Installation</h2>
      <p>Create the folder where you want to have your project files. Then right click on it
         and select <code>TortoiseSVN → Checkout…</code>. Enter the URL to checkout, in this case  <code>https://gtsvn.uit.no/langtech/trunk</code> and click on <code>OK</code>. The files are then downloaded to the folder.
      </p>
      <p>In order to be able to check in, fill in your username and password.</p>
      <p></p>
      <h2>Usage</h2>
      <p>When the program is installed, go to the folder where you want to keep the language
         technology files (e.g. <code>My Documents</code>). In that folder, right-click with the mouse on an empty spot in the folder. You
         will note that the context-sensitive menu has some additions in the middle, where
         it reads SVN and something. Choose the <code>SVN Checkout</code>. You will then get a panel, where you fill in your account data.
      </p>
      <p>Now you may edit the files, e.g. with <code>EditPad Lite</code> or <code>XMLEditor</code>. When you have edited them you will note that the green symbol attached to the file
         symbol has turned orange. This means you should <code>check in</code>. Right click on the file icon, and choose <code>check in</code>. Write a log message, and click OK.
      </p>
      <p>The general principles are the same for SVN usage here as elsewhere: Always update
         before you start working (right-click, and SVN Update), and always check in when you
         are done with your work, minimum once a day.
      </p>
      <p>There also is a <a href="http://tortoisesvn.net/docs/nightly/TortoiseSVN_en/index.html">Extensive user guide</a> .
      </p>
      <p>Key chapters include:</p>
      <ul>
         <li><a href="http://tortoisesvn.net/docs/nightly/TortoiseSVN_en/tsvn-dug-checkout.html">Check out the files for the first time"</a></li>
         <li><a href="http://tortoisesvn.net/docs/nightly/TortoiseSVN_en/tsvn-dug-commit.html">Check in your work to the central repository"</a></li>
         <li><a href="http://tortoisesvn.net/docs/nightly/TortoiseSVN_en/tsvn-dug-update.html">Update the working copy, or check out files</a></li>
      </ul>
   </body>
</html>