<html xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en">
   <head>
      <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8">
      <title>SubEthaEdit</title>
   </head>
   <body>
      <h1>About SubEthaEdit (SEE)</h1>
      <p>SubEthaEdit, named after a famous net in The Hitchhiker's guide to the galaxy (SubEthaNet
         — long before
         Internet was invented), is a standard text editor, just like TextEdit, NotePad, or
         whatever - <em>except</em>
         that it allows instant and easy collaboration and concurrent editing. What you see
         is what the other person
         does - WYSIWTOPD - instantly, everywhere. It is perfect for writing meeting memos
         together, for debugging
         together, for collaborative article writing etc. Getting the other buddy into your
         document is as easy as
         drag-and-drop.
      </p>
      <p>We have bought a site version of SubEthaEdit for this project. Talk to Trond.</p>
      <p>You can also download a 30-day trial from the <a href="http://www.codingmonkeys.de/subethaedit/">SEE
            website</a>, or try out <a href="http://www.codingmonkeys.de/subethaedit/old.html">the free 2.2 version of
            SEE</a> (which unfortunately doesn't seem to be compatible with the latest versions of MacOS
         X (Lion and Snow
         Leopard).
      </p>
      <h1>SEE server</h1>
      <p>We have installed SubEthaEdit on our main server, such that a number of shared documents
         are always
         available for everyone to use. This is especially nice when everyone collaborating
         is behind a firewall or NAT.
         Just click on the following link: <a href="see://divvun.no">see://divvun.no</a>.
      </p>
      <h1>SubEthaEdit settings</h1>
      <p>Under the first menu (SubEthaEdit), choose "preferences", and the tab "Editing". "Default
         encoding" should
         be "UTF-8" and "Line endings" should be "Unix (LF)". "Highligth Syntax", "Show matching
         brackets", "Show line
         numbers" and "Wrap lines by word" are nice choices as well.
      </p>
      <p>On the "Printing" tab, "Show line numbers" is a good choice.</p>
      <p>On the "Advanced" tabs, install the command line tools.</p>
      <h1>Syntax modes</h1>
      <p>We have made a number of modes available for the formal languages we use, like <code>twolc</code>,
         <code>xfst</code>, <code>lexc</code> etc. Have a look in <code>$GTHOME/tools/see-tools/</code>. These modes
         will help you in editing the most common document formats in use. A number of other
         modes are available from
         the <a href="http://www.codingmonkeys.de/subethaedit/modes.html">SEE modes page</a>.
      </p>
      <h1>Usage</h1>
      <p>Basic usage of SubEthaEdit requires no tutorial. Just write, erase, and move around
         with the arrow keys. But
         SubEthaEdit may be a much more efficient tool. Here are some hints:
      </p>
      <ul>
         <li>Most basic emacs commands work in SubEthaEdit. Cf. the list below, where "C-a" means
            "hold down the
            <code>ctrl </code>key and press <code>A</code>"
            <ul>
               <li><strong>C-a, C-e, C-p, C-n:
                     </strong><br>Beginning of line, end of line, previous line, next line
               </li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li><strong>C-k, C-d:
                     </strong><br>Delete the rest of the line, delete the next character
               </li>
            </ul>
         </li>
         <li>Ordinary Macintosh commands work (command and then x, c, v, z, a for cut, copy, paste,
            undo and select
            all
         </li>
         <li>The Find/Replace command supports <em>regular expressions</em></li>
         <li>Have a look at the "Settings" options in the SubEthaEdit menu. Make "Show line numbers"
            and "Show
            matching parenthese" default.
         </li>
      </ul>
      <h1>SubEthaEdit as a collaborative editor</h1>
      <p>This is where SEE really shines, even today, with a lot of online pastebins available.
         You may invite other
         people into your document. Do as follows:
      </p>
      <ol>
         <li>On the top of the document, press the yellow <strong>Announce</strong> symbol on the top left corner of
            the document (or press <strong>Cmd-Shift-E</strong>).
         </li>
         <li>In the pop-up window to the right, your name will appear. Above it, change Locked
            to
            <strong>Read/Write</strong> (or press <strong>Cmd-Shift-A</strong>).
         </li>
         <li>Make the <strong>Connections</strong> window visible by going to <strong>Windows &gt;
               Connections</strong> (or by pressing <strong>Cmd-K</strong>).
         </li>
         <li>To invite other SEE users to your document, <strong>EITHER</strong>:
            <ul>
               <li>drag their <strong>iChat</strong> buddy icon to the <strong>Connections</strong> window - SEE will
                  prepare a chat with the correct SEE link; <strong>OR</strong>:
               </li>
               <li>drag the blue ball <em>from</em> the <strong>Connections</strong> window <em>to</em> an existing
                  chat or other communications channel - a clickable link will appear where you drop
                  the ball
               </li>
            </ul>
         </li>
      </ol>
   </body>
</html>