<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>SubEthaEdit</title>

    <authors>
      <person email="sjurnm@mac.com" name="Sjur Moshagen" />
      <person email="trond.trosterud@uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>About SubEthaEdit</title>

      <p>SubEthaEdit, named after a famous net in The Hitchhiker's guide to
      the galaxy (SubEthaNet — long before Internet was invented), and is a
      standard text editor, just like TextEdit, NotePad, or
      whatever.</p>

      <p>We have bought a site version of SubEthaEdit for this project. Talk
      to Trond.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>SubEthaEdit settings</title>

      <p>Under the first menu (SubEthaEdit), choose "preferences", and the tab
      "Editing". "Default encoding" should be "UTF-8" and "Line endings"
      should be "Unix (LF)". "Highligth Syntax", "Show matching brackets",
      "Show line numbers" and "Wrap lines by word" are nice choices as
      well.</p>

      <p>On the "Printing" tab, "Show line numbers" is a good choice.</p>

      <p>On the "Advanced" tabs, install the command line tools.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Usage</title>

      <p>Basic usage of SubEthaEdit requires no tutorial. Just write, erase,
      and move around with the arrow keys. But SubEthaEdit may be a much more
      efficient tool. Here are some hints:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>Most basic emacs commands work in SubEthaEdit. Cf. the list below,
        where "C-a" means "hold down the <code>ctrl </code>key and press
        <code>A</code>"<dl>
            <dt>C-a, C-e, C-p, C-n</dt>

            <dd>Beginning of line, end of line, previous line, next line</dd>
          </dl><dl>
            <dt>C-k, C-d</dt>

            <dd>Delete the rest of the line, delete the next character</dd>
          </dl></li>

        <li>Ordinary Macintosh commands work (command and then x, c, v, z, a
        for cut, copy, paste, undo and select all</li>

        <li>The Find/Replace command supports regular expressions</li>

        <li>Have a look at the "Settings" options in the SubEthaEdit menu.
        Make "Show line numbers" and "Show matching parenthese" default.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>SubEthaEdit as a distributed editor</title>

      <p>You may invite other people into your document. Do as follows:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>On the top of the document, press the yellow Announce symbol on
        the top left corner of the document.</li>

        <li>In the pop-up window to the right, your name will appear. Above
        it, change Locked to Read/Write</li>

        <li>Find you IP-number (if you have the program IPMenu, it is there,
        or eventually, in the Terminal, write ifconfig, and pick the number
        following the text inet.</li>

        <li>Give it to the ones you want to invite, in the form
        see//123.123.123.123/. They may click on it, and they will then appear
        in the document.</li>
      </ol>

      <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by
      $Author$</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>