<html xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en">
   <head>
      <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8">
      <title>MS Office Hyphenation Documentation</title>
   </head>
   <body>
      <p>Hyphenation is provided for both supported languages, North and Lule
         Sámi, and is installed automatically together with the spellers. See the
         <a href="http://divvun.no/korrektur/korrektur.html">page dedicated to
            proofing tools installation</a> for further details.
      </p>
      <h1>Basic architecture</h1>
      <p>Technically, the hyphenation engines and lexicons are the same as in
         the InDesign installation, and the engines are delivered by Polderland.
         The hyphenation lexicons are compiled by the Divvun project for the
         Polderland engine.
      </p>
      <p>The hyphenation tool consists of the following components:</p>
      <ul>
         <li>a hyphenation engine</li>
         <li>a word-list lexicon with compounding support</li>
         <li>a pattern-based fall-back component for unrecognised words</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The word-list lexicon is generated from our transducer sources, and
         is exactly the same as the speller lexicon (which contains hyphenation
         points). The hyphenation points are mostly added by a rule-based
         component, with exceptional hyphenation explicitly added to the lexicon
         entries. The hyphenator can be tested independently on <a href="http://giellatekno.uit.no/cgi/d-smj.eng.html">this page</a>.
      </p>
      <p>This means that all words recognised by the speller should hyphenate
         correctly - always. And all other words should hyphenate correctly in
         most cases. All in all the hyphenation precision should be around 99,9 %
         or better. Anything else is a bug, and should be reported to us via <a href="mailto:feedback@divvun.no">e-mail</a> or <a href="http://giellatekno.uit.no/bugzilla">Bugzilla</a>.
      </p>
   </body>
</html>